You are listening to Ancient Faith Radio, Orthodox Christianity for today's world.
He will be a staff for the righteous with which for them to stand and not to fall, and
he will be the light of the nations and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him, and they will praise and bless
and celebrate with song the Lord of S-
spirits. 1st denoc, chapter 48, verses 4 through 5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge but is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels,
demons, and saints. In our time, many year into break free of the prison of a flat, secular
materialism, to see and to know reality as it truly is. What is this spiritual reality
like? How do we engage with it well? How do we permeate everyday life with spiritual
Presence.
Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick, and Father Stephen DeYoung,
host this live Colin show focused on enchantment in creation, the union of the scene and unseen
as made by God and experienced by mankind throughout history. Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Hey, good evening, giant killers, dragon slayers, cockroach and croters. You are listening to the
Lord of Spirits podcast. My co-host Father Stephen DeYoung, the Maccabeeus of the monstrous,
is would be straight from the swamp and laugh yet Louisiana.
And I'm father and just human damage Pennsylvania purchased precariously atop the arcane tower of podcasting
hovering dozens of stories dozens above a disused gateway to the underworld
I think you're a lot of old Hogi shop
Actually actually dramatic about it actually
Actually my building not only used to be
apparently a furniture factory in showroom, but there actually was a
a mortuary funeral home and cream it.
Torium down in the basement. So I'm not, yeah, I'm not completely embellishing way beyond reality here. So it is true. It is true.
We're live, everybody. And if you are listening to us live, you can call us at 855-237-2346. And you can talk to us.
And we're going to get your calls in the second half of the show if you make them.
And our very own, our truly beloved Matyska Trudy, the tank Richter, will be taking your
calls.
Are you troubled by strange noises in the middle of the night?
Do you experience feelings of dread in your basement erratic?
Have you or any of your family ever seen a spook-fest specter or ghost?
If the answer is yes, then don't wait another minute, pick up your phone and call the professionals.
Tonight we're talking about demonic activity in the world, including temptation, torment, and yes, even possession.
So Father Stephen, aside from your own trollish self, is your house currently haunted by anything?
No
Oh well
Success see I live across the street from a graveyard so like
The ghosts are all wherever they died. No
People don't die in the cemetery usually not usually not usually
It's atypical for that
dying to get in as we have seen some fights break out. Oh
Oh, that's it. It's super classy
You eat your cousin getting in a brawl
Do they do? Do they do like-
New Orleans. Do they do those funerals with the guys walking along with the coffin and playing a band?
We haven't got, we've got some kind of low, a couple of low grade versions, but not the super high
quality. What's you get in New Orleans? Oh, oh, oh. We have, by the way, we have people
sounding off from St. Louis, Missouri, a guy who claims to be a twin peak guy. He is in Missouri.
I hear they love company also from East Tennessee. I'm not sure.
exactly where that is, Longview, Texas.
Somebody who love you, Texas.
Yes. Yes.
A place where I spent many years.
Lisa. Yes. Lisa Jones.
Is this someone you actually know?
But that's what Lisa, that's not really a big.
The Jones not ring any bell.
It's a long time ago. I'm an elderly man.
So someone, someone listening from right here in Pennsylvania, maybe
there's somewhere in my building coming from inside the house.
All is coming.
Yeah, see I
Congratulations on the local sports ball victory.
Yes.
You're welcome.
Oh, someone coming from Wisconsin.
Is this one?
Wisconsin, the part of Wisconsin where they say the say milk rather than milk.
I don't know.
Oh, we've got someone come listening from Sweden, Huntsville, Alabama, New York City.
New York City at the end of romper room.
New York's, you know, the only thing that stands between me and New York City is New
Jersey, which I mean, that's quite the barrier.
But you can go around.
get in the laskin
Someone in the Blue Ridge Mountains, hey Blue Ridge Mountains, that's God's God's own green
earth right there.
North Carolina, the Rockies, Wal-Norke Port, Pennsylvania.
Hey, that's actually just up the road from me.
O'Lisa says that she doesn't know you personally.
Someone from Westside, God Virginia.
Wow.
See, I start mentioning where people are from and then everybody's got to go.
Did they all want to get?
I know.
Northern Virginia.
That's not really Virginia.
kid.
So what are we talking about tonight?
Well, demons.
So I know you can watch your local team's sports ball victory.
I heard there was some kind of altercation with a pointy ball this past weekend, but there
were a number of things.
I could boil it down for the number of things I learned watching the Super Bowl and the
commercials.
Oh, what did you learn?
So I learned that Snoop Dog and...
Oh, what's his face now his name went right out of my head Tom Brady. Oh, that stoop dog and Tom Brady hate each other
Long line again or is he back to just now get for a long list of reasons. There's a whole list of reasons
Why really like some kind of ongoing feud?
Two commercials where they list just all the reasons they hate each other
Okay, and it has something to do with them being anti-Semitic
I don't even know how that works either of them are Jewish.
But back in my stage and days actually I worked. I think it was the last. Yes, it was the last.
One of the last stops of the last year, the first run of Lala Paloza. Snoop Dogg was there.
Snoop Dogg was there as well as on the side stage. And I don't know who came up with this.
but there was a band's name, the orb, another one called
Orbit and then yet another called orbital.
And you can't tell me that was not a purpose.
I bet those bands probably hated, hated that.
But they probably hated each other.
Yes. Yes.
Like there's a big feud.
I also learned that if you happen to be born with a skull shaped like a cowboy head.
Right.
You shouldn't be too sad.
It'll be okay because Westerns will come back in style.
I guess these are references that I would have had to actually watch.
this uh and and most importantly most importantly from the half-time show I learned
that all of us can take solace no matter how bad your life gets you can think to yourself
it could be worse I could be Drake
dudes having another bad year already
So these are the important things for any
any of our other lists. I think there may have been a low rate of super bowl viewing among
our listenership for some reason. So here's the question that I'm going to put out there
for the chat. Let people weigh in on this while we begin to have this discussion about
spirits once again. Is Tinkerbell an Egregor? I'm just putting that out there for you in the chat
on YouTube. Is Tinkerbell an Egregor? Sound off. Let us know what you think. Because yeah, just
putting that out there. Alright, there's a different version.
of Tinkerbell is that relevant at all?
I mean, none of them are that old.
Like Julia Roberts, Tinkerbell versus...
That's true. You have to clap to make sure she exists.
Animated Tinkerbell.
I know. Tinkerbell is a murderer.
I'm just putting that out there by the way.
Yeah. You got kind of a grudge.
Did something happen to you as a child while you were watching
a wonderful world of Disney on the weekend?
I could be like during the intro and now you're Tinkerbell.
Take her back home. Take her back home.
I'm not sure.
I'm telling Wendy.
So anyway, yeah, we're talking about demons.
Yep.
Yep, demon.
Not necessarily tinkerbell.
Tinkerbell might be a demon.
Although, I guess there's a pole going on now.
Yeah.
People are like, what's an nigger Gore?
Come on, don't make me Google that for you.
Go, go, yeah, go bother pageral about that.
Oh man, one person says tinkerbell is a succubus.
Okay, that's, that's a self-tell that we don't want to go down.
Don't ask if...
many.
I know that's going to follow up with.
I know.
Yeah.
Okay.
Sorry.
Sorry, everybody.
Yeah.
So, you know, we're talking about demons.
And so we're going to start by, as is our want with a little review.
Yes.
Pull together some threads from some, some older episodes, which even if you listen to, if
If you listen to them in any semblance of order, you listen to a long time ago.
just because there are a lot of hours of Lord of Spirits between us now and then. So when we talk
about so demons are all of the demons, all of the things we're going to be talking about under
this subheading demons is itself subheadings of the category of spirits. Right. Right. And so when we
We talk about spirits as a reminder, we're talking...
about consciousness above the human level. And what we've talked about, what we mean by that is we've
talked about how contrary to say 19th century worldviews where they thought, and previous where
they thought that animals were just sort of mechanistic machines that didn't have feelings or emotions
or consciousness, we now know for certain that they do. I mean anyone who has had a pet, well most pets,
some patch, sure. You know, but...
got to pet a guana or something, you know, um, you're the snake guy. Um, maybe not. But if you've had,
you know, traditional animals, you know that they have some level of consciousness. Uh,
either a fun loving, warm consciousness, like a dog or a hateful, spiteful evil consciousness,
like a cat, but they have, they have some level of, uh, of consciousness. So there are levels of
of consciousness sort of
below human consciousness. Right? There are ideas and concepts and things that humans can comprehend
that they can't. Right? But consciousness is not just zero or one. Right? And so we're talking
about spirits, we're talking about levels of consciousness that are above the human level.
Right? And part of what that means also, that above,
is that
And we've talked about this in terms of your own body.
Your own human body is a composite of organs and organ systems and bacteria that are actually
separate life forms and all kinds of other things, sort of subsystems that operate according
to their own regulation.
therefore have some some cases very low level of consciousness yet.
It's not like you sit and argue with your spleen, you know, or you have to tell your heart
to work, right?
That the human consciousness is itself in a way not really a gestalt consciousness, but
a higher order, the sense that it encompasses those lower level consciousnesses in our
organs and the organisms that make our bodies function biologically.
If you're in the same room with someone, you're gut-flora or communicating with theirs,
chemically.
I know.
It's so creepy.
It's...
Not as creepy as the Mountain Dew Seal commercial, but you didn't see that either.
Anyway.
It's so...
Is there a round?
I don't know.
No, it was him.
Okay.
They put his face onto the body of an actual seal.
Wow.
He's a AI.
It was sort of a body horror thing.
It was like a sequel to Tusk but they were trying to-
to sell me Mountain Dew. Anyway, so, so levels of consciousness above ours act upon and interact
with human consciousness, the way human consciousness interacts with those lower levels of consciousness
that we were just talking about. And we're going to get into more of what that means as we go.
So if you're like, whoa, right, you don't have to necessarily stop listening and go back and
listen to the what is a spirit episode right?
we're going to get back into this. But yes, this is a little bit of catch up so that
we're at least, you know, you know, what page we're going to be working from. And of
course, spirits are part of the noetic world. The world that's perceived by the news, sometimes
translated as the mind. We're going to talk more about that in the second half. What exactly
that means. So don't, you know, if you're not up to speed on that, don't worry. We'll get
to back up to speed in the...
in the second half, but they exist in the world of the mind of thoughts, right? Meaning
we don't primarily interact with them in a physical and material way. The primary way
you interact with demons is not by seeing them or touching them or physically wrestling
with them.
Right.
I mean, that's the, I think that's the stereotype that a lot of people have of like, that's what
demonic activity is. Maybe because it's like, that's the way it goes in movies, you know, or whatever.
Like, end of days where our short-sager shoots the devil with a grenade launcher.
Right. Who can forget that class?
You know what his character's name is in that movie?
No, I don't remember. Like, no, it remembers the name of like any of, you know,
I don't know.
It's a baby queer.
from a total recall because you got the quaid get off of Ma's but this is just
shorts and anger right but his his carriages that he's like a tough retired cop
in end of days whose name is Jericho Kane oh nice completely believable
well anyway yes you can't actually do spiritual warfare with a rocket launcher
Perhaps unfortunately.
But yeah, that doesn't work.
You could talk about someone wrestling with their demons, but you're speaking of it in a different sense.
Not an untrue sense, not an unreal sense, but a different sense.
So, to put a finer on it, point on it, what's a demon?
We talked about this way back in the long ago time.
I mean, just some of our earliest stuff.
Yeah, yeah, that's why we're reviewing a lot of this stuff is from like the first few episodes.
So 2020, you know, different world that was.
My power went out halfway through the episode.
I know.
So I mean, you probably didn't even get this the first time.
Yeah.
But so what?
Right.
What is the demon?
So of course, originally we're talking about the word day, mon in Greek, which technically
means something like an ancestral spirit. The way that term is used is closely
related to the way that the oaths that we translate as God, with either a lower
case or a capital G. The way it's used, in fact there's overlap. There's
overlap. There's not always a super clear distinction between the two.
Sometimes those terms are used for the same being and it's distinguished based on activity
and that kind of thing.
On the whole, in general, generally, there's tons of exceptions to this, but in general,
Deimos is used to refer to a lower level.
If somebody is using both the term Tha-O's or Tha-E, the plural, we'll talk about gods,
And then also talking about demoness, right?
Demon.
as we would translate it, the demoness is referring to a lower level of beings than the beings
that they're referring to as fey, as God.
Yeah, kind of in rated lesser spirits.
Right.
Now, again, there's tons of exceptions, though.
Like there are places where Zeus is referred to as a day-bone.
Sure.
Right.
And what's going on there is not purely that the words were interchangeable.
that there's
a memory there of a couple things, one being that Zeus has like three birthplaces. So there
are actual ancient Greek kings who were sort of assimilated into Zeus, right, into this
Thunder God. So there's this memory of him being this ancestral spirit, right, being this,
having been this sort of ancient king at some point in the distant murky ancestral past.
then also.
So there's the memory of a member, there's the Titans, including his father, Cronus, or
Cronus.
And then there are the Olympians who are the children of the Titans.
And so in that relationship, right, the Titans would be the higher order or the more ancient
or the greater level of spirits and the Olympians would be the lesser.
So there's a connection there too.
So when you find Zeus or Apollo being referred to as day mode,
it's usually in some context where that memory is an issue somehow or is in the background.
So that means that in
Purely Greek contacts, right in pagan Greek tongue contacts. There was not a negative. There's not a sense of appropriate
Amattach to that word
Right when you say demon to someone now they instantly think evil
Yeah, yeah, I mean
You know and a lot of like ancient Greek texts
Someone said I have a demon that would be like saying I have a special wise person who tells me important things
Yeah, like Saki knows.
was different to the second.
According to the second.
Yeah.
Right.
He was very happy about that.
Yeah.
So, that was not necessarily a negative thing.
It becomes a negative thing in a Christian context.
The term doesn't get used a lot in Greek second temple Jewish writings.
that sometimes.
Once you get to the Greek period, not just like people writing in Greek, but
Post Alexander the Great, right?
You start you start getting it used to refer to what or otherwise referred to as for example unclean spirits
More commonly, but
It's really in the Christian context
So for example, when St. Paul says with
the nation sacrificed, they sacrificed to demons and not to God, right? To demonis. Yeah.
And not to God singular. That's a, it's an own on his unpolished part, like saying,
you guys sacrificed to lesser spirits. Yeah. Well, but also so a pagan would kind of have
to agree with that. Right. Yeah, sure, sure. Yeah, yeah, we're children of a lot. Yeah,
we do. Not to the God of Israel. We're not sacrificing to the God of Israel. Yeah. We're
sacrificing to the day bonus, right?
it. So it's kind of an incontrovertible point. Right. And so because of that distinction,
right, because with this rent of Christianity, the worship of demonus becomes a thing opposed
to the worship of the true God, the capital G God, then demonus takes on this negative
character. Right. And that's why we now think of it in that way. Right.
And in fact, this causes a lot of confusion if you start trying to look into the Jewish
understanding of what we would call demons.
Because as we've talked about on the show before, the inocic tradition and the stuff about
fallen angels gets repudiated very early during the period of the formation of Christianity,
that all
ready by the time you get to St. Justin's dialogue with Trifo. Trifo is saying, you know,
Yucufi Christians think that angels rebelled against God. Right. Because, and it is true
that now Orthodoxy is that there are no angels rebelled against God. So the beings that
we would consider demons, even the unclean spirits and this kind of thing are not considered
to be spirit.
in rebellion against God in a Jewish context, they're just considered to be angels. The same as
angels, they're just spirits like angels are. They all do God's bidding. Just some of God's bidding
is unpleasant from our perspective. Yeah. And so there's a very different, right? But that
develops out of we've talked about this in the context of the Old Testament. They're not getting
that out of nowhere, right? We've talked about the sort of
Old Testament Theodicy that these demonic powers, these spiritual powers of evil that are
at work in the world, God sort of has them on a leash, right? And makes them do his bidding,
right? And so the current Jewish view develops out of that. If you take that and you strip away
the inocic tradition and the way in which those traditions find their way into the New Testament,
That's what you're left with.
Right, so that's the reason for that disagreement, but they still don't have that understanding
of sort of spirits that have rebelled against God.
That's been sort of they've sort of excised those inocent ideas from their tradition.
and it's fair to say X-sized.
There are some cases...
where orthodox Judaism is just continuing the sect of the Pharisees, right?
The Pharisees obviously had their own particular beliefs, and so there are some
things that the Pharisees sort of never really fully accepted. There are other
things that a first century Pharisee would have been comfortable with. See, for
example, St. Paul, that a third century orthodox Jew would have become much more
uncomfortable with.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, like things within the Jewish tradition. Yeah, so like those are the things that type of
multiple persons of God, for instance. Yeah, yeah, multiple the idea of multiple persons of God, the
the uh, and of course, um, this, right? The idea of rebellious or fallen angels. Yeah, yeah.
So that said, um, again, this is one of our very early episodes, but we talked about
the different angelic rebellions.
Plural. Hopefully by now, as this shows now, I've been running for a few years. Hopefully,
most of our listeners who aren't brand new listeners have put Milton out of their minds
because John Milton was a bit out of his mind. He was a pure and a little messier head.
this idea that, you know, well, there's a whole nexus of I-
ideas there. There was some before God created the earth, there was some primordial fall of
Satan and a bunch of demons into hell, the idea that Satan like rules hell, instead of
being imprisoned there. I mean, even in Dante's in Ferno, he's in prison there. Right?
Like this whole idea that he rules there and he's sort of this in show almost romantic,
political revolution area or something.
Um, that's all, uh, uh, Miltonian nonsense, right?
You could enjoy his prose.
You could enjoy his, I'm not big on English lit, but feel free to enjoy his prose as fiction.
Uh, feel free to enjoy his fiction.
Uh, but in his fiction, there's no,
In fact, it's a lot of people grew up.
even people who grew up in churches who say everything they teach is based on the Bible.
Being taught that, even though it's nowhere in the Bible.
So we talked about how these angelic rebellions are things that are connected, that begin after
the creation of the world.
We could give the Saint Andrew of Crete quote again in his commentary on the book of Revelation,
series talking about Revelation chapter 12 and the
fall of the devil, he says we must accept as all the fathers teach that after the creation of the
world the devil fell through envy. The church fathers have various days, various creation days to
which they link the creation of the angels, mostly the first day and the fourth day, though there's a
minority report for the second day. But the idea being that the angelic creation happens as part
of the creation of the world. And the beginning of Angelic rebellion with the devil begins
in Genesis 3. Right. Right. And it's connected that rebellion. We're going to deal with this
some more both in tonight's episode and in our follow up episode two weeks from now.
that because of that these angelic rebellions again we don't know what it's like to be an angel.
Don't know what it's like to be a bat. You don't know what it's like to be an angel. So we don't know
how angels experience time since they don't have bodies and they don't age. They don't have
material bodies like ours at least. They don't age, right? They don't experience
materiality in the same way. They don't experience flux of change. So how they experience time we don't know.
Yeah, all we can see is
what we can see. You know, I mean, it's just like, you know, you and I can have lunch.
I don't know what it's like to be you. I can see you eating your lunch. I can see you,
you know, here you're talking to me, but I don't know what it's like to be you. You don't
know what it's like to be. Let's get to the point. I can't say the next line. Yeah. No,
You may not.
Sir.
Um.
Yes.
So.
Yes, so
But so these these angelic rebellions right are connected to and manifest
themselves at certain points in human history. Right and but we're putting it
that way because to say that okay so the devil fell on the day that Adam fell
whether or not we know what day that is right Matthew Henry could tell you exactly
that we went day of the week that was.
I'm just dunking on Puritans tonight for no reason.
But whatever day that was, that's the day the devil fell.
Right?
The problem with that kind of thinking is that kind of absolutizes time in the sense
that, right, God and everybody created, right, like experiences the flow of time in the same way.
Right, so like God creates on the third day of the third day was April third, 4,000, 4 BC or something, right?
That's when God created all the animals boom, right
That misses the point and and this isn't a modern thing. This is St. Augustine makes this point
Right, he says what does it mean to say that God did something on a day? Yeah
Yeah, like he wasn't doing it before.
Or that he stopped doing it.
And a tick is calendar, right?
And he didn't, right?
Like, doesn't follow.
But we could say, we could say that God's actions, the divine activities, right?
God's actions manifest themselves in our human experience in particular times and places.
Right?
So part of God's creation of the world was creating me.
Okay. But I was born on June 16, 1975 and presumably conceived nine months earlier. Are you sure
you didn't like incubate for ten months? I said presumably. I just put that out. Plus
it's give or take nine months. I think I was late. But anyway. Yeah. I came out weighing
ten pounds and with teeth. No lie. I was born with teeth. Whoa. See, that suddenly feeds
into the whole Nephilim.
Yeah, yeah, the folk tales and legends continue to grow but that is a true fact you can ask my mother
I
Will ask your mother. I know your mom. She will verify this
She was the victim of it
But more woman
But anyway
You go back ten months before that and I didn't exist right
So did God create me at the moment I was conceived or
did God just create me? And then that was the moment in time when I came into being in the
world of the material world that we all experience. Right? That's the distinction we're making.
Yeah.
Because otherwise you could have a real hard time reconciling God created the world and everything
in it in six days. Right. And then synchronizing that with...
He created you and me and the tree in my backyard and the grass.
Right. If he created that during the six days that he can have also created on this day,
if you're going to absolute times.
Absolutely. It's time.
So angelic actions likewise sort of manifest themselves to us humans in terms of our human
experience in human history at some particular point in time.
And in one of our early episodes, you could tell based on the title, there are actually five-ish
times when angelic beings fell. Yeah. Yeah. The issue, the issue being it might have, it might have
been one being falling two different times or it could be two different beings. Right. Yeah. Right.
So you can go back and listen.
of that episode if you want. Right? Some more detail on that. But again, these are just reminders.
Though and all of those, the point here though being for tonight, all of those angelic beings
from all of those four or five episodes that it says, those are all things that get called demons.
Right. So the devil is referred to as a demon, the Prince of Demons. Right.
It's got a thing, the other demons who fall, right?
who are referred to by as the watchers, the angels who left their former estate in the time of Noah,
right? For the New Testament, those are referred to as demons. So demon gets used for sort of all
of those beings. Demon also gets used. And hopefully as the show goes on, this will get less and
less controversial because this is just a thing. Demon is also used to refer to the spirits of
certain dead humans.
And these dead humans,
regardless of who they are,
who are referred to as demons,
are the sort of children of those fallen angelic beings.
That does not mean literally.
Well, it does not mean in the biological sense.
Right.
It is literal, but not biological.
Biologically literal.
Yeah.
Yeah, because for example.
you're adopted children are really your children.
Yeah. Right. But they're not biologically your children.
Your dogs are not your children. Your cats are not your children.
No, my dogs are my dogs. People.
My dogs are my dog.
One of them is an alien. One of them I'm not sure is actually species canis.
I'm convinced one of them is a cat that one of your dogs.
My dog with me just a kind of a really long series of bizarre behaviors.
And they found her wandering in the woods literally.
So like I kind of think her people way of laughter,
but then flown back home.
So where we're talking about their children, right?
The obvious thing, because people get excited,
people are probably running to is the Nephilim.
And this is true, right?
This is a case.
And as we've talked about on the show,
that also is not saying that these are the biological
and of angels and humans, but these are children that were born through demonic sexual ritual.
Yes.
Involving two humans, at least.
Yes, to be a bit euphemistic.
But this also includes various other figures referred to as the sons of predation.
You don't have to have been born from that.
A lot of times people think, oh...
Okay, so yeah, it was this ritual.
So they tried to sort of backdoor
a biological definition that way.
Right.
So like any kid who was born out of one of those rituals
is just faded to become this demonic evil.
Yeah, because apparently magic is real.
Like magical formulas actually apparently do work.
Yeah.
But yeah.
Right.
But there is a participation going on
that we're gonna talk about more tonight.
Yeah.
And so there are other people who...
We're not born out of any kind of ritual like that per se.
Right.
But who through participation with demons become the sons of those demonic beings, right?
Exactly.
Talk about sonship.
The image, right?
And participants.
I mean, Jesus says to some of the leaders of the Judean leaders of his time and place that
they are sons of the devil.
And he does not mean by that that they were born from, you know.
and they get rituals. But that they were as evil as those who were. Right. Right.
Of old. Um, right. And of course, there's the St. John Chrysostom quote that we've given
several times on the show. Yeah, which basically he says, you know, some people say that if you
get, if you die in a violent way, then you become a demon after death. That's not how you become
a demon after death. You become a demon after death by living like a demon before death.
Right, it's to paraphrase.
right? Yeah, he's sort of answering the belief that kind of still exists, although it's ghosts,
right? Yeah. That someone dies of violent death in sort of their spirit, looks for revenge,
or haunts the place or something. There are people who believe that, who he was preaching to.
He says, that's not how you become a demon. You become a demon by living like a demon. That's not
how this works. And so, right, this category of demons begins with, right, the Nephilim and those
destroyed by the flood, but this includes figures ever since, right?
Judas is referred to as the Son of Perdition, right, which is language picked up
from the book of Jubiles to refer to the Nephilim. Yeah, yeah. And as we've
talked about relatively recently compared to this other stuff on the show, a
demonized person like this is sort of an anti-Saint. Right? We talk about
Let's say
not being the opposite of sinner, but saint being the opposite of demon.
Right? And we'll talk more about the saint side of that in a couple of weeks here.
But so as we just alluded to,
right, there's a distinction in Saint John,
Christophe was making it in his own day in the fifth century
between sort of popular ghost ideas and
demons, right? And a question we get from time to time, fairly frequent, not as much as
we used to, but we get questions about ghosts.
I was saying knowledge is getting out there.
We get questions about ghosts and haunted things and different experiences.
as people have had with ghosts, meaning like the spirits of the dead. Not so much spirits
of dead loved ones, but things that are more like St. John Chrysostom was talking about.
Oh, so less like Patrick's Wazey and more like the other guy.
Yeah, it's like, you know, there's this house or this building or this basement or this
place in the woods where some person or person's, you know, uh,
Does Asian faith try and monetize this on YouTube?
I don't remember.
I think so.
I think it actually.
Well, not anymore.
So we're somewhat committed to a side.
And people say, oh, when you go there, it's haunted by the spirits of those troubled
souls, right?
Yeah.
Still, right?
That kind of thing, where it's sort of activity or experiences that you wouldn't
call angelic or positive, right? But also don't seem to the people to be necessarily
demonic, at least as they understand demons, right? We have to remember also that demons
can be subtle, right? Demons are not just all cackling jobs running around trying to make
every person do the most evil thing possible all the time. Right?
That was another question we've gotten is, you know, if these pagan parts of the world,
they're still worshiping demons, right?
How do they have any kind of functioning society?
And it's like, well, because demons play a long game, right?
They're not stupid lunatics, right?
and you can subvert whole generations of people to evil and destroy them.
You know, the way they do, as opposed to just, we're going to blow the whole thing up in
one giant death and destruction in one generation.
So, what you understand is that in addition to the actual spirits involved, angelic or demonic
experience and there's not there's not really a third category of spirit.
Sorry everybody.
Yeah, a lot of people want there to be a third category of spirit because they're into
fairies or something.
Yeah, I mean, yeah, like this idea of neutral spirits, you know, like, oh, they're not taking
sides.
I'm like, that's not a thing because God created everything to do what He created it
to do.
And so you're either obeying what God made you to do, or you're not.
You know, it can't be like, no.
I'm gonna kind of go off and do my own.
Hurry Shakespeare fans.
Yeah, yeah.
I mean, when I tell people, they're like,
but there's all these stories that,
but I'm like, yes, they are stories
and they function in the stories
for a particular reason,
narratively within the story.
But if we're talking about real spirits in the real world,
not just stories, again,
they're all created by God,
they're doing what God told them to do,
maybe them for or they're not doing that.
So there's no third option.
Yeah.
I'd have to study this a lot more and I'm not going to because I'm not that interested.
I think a lot of those kinds of stories actually emerge
in the early modern era.
So, are you have real neutrality?
Yeah, yeah. I think, you know, the stuff that I'm familiar with that's on the medieval side of things,
the way that it sometimes
gets played out and I only discovered this because, well, you can imagine, the way it gets played out
is that a fairy will actually ask a priest, believe it or not, whether they can be saved
and the priest will respond, well, we'll find that out at the end of time, basically.
So the context of that kind of encounter, right, is not like true neutrality.
It's, it's significant.
Pretty good bury as if it's like an animal.
Yeah, yeah, exactly.
animal. Exactly. Exactly. Right. So, so, you know, I'm not aware of any, at least within the Christian
tradition and, you know, like Jewish stuff, I'm not aware of anything earlier than that. But I mean,
again, I was like, you I have not made a serious study of it. It would be an interesting. It seems
to be like when you get into the early modern period, and I mean the very early modern period,
about like the 16th century. Yeah, sure. You start getting this desire to bring back some of the
the pagan spirits and not see them as demons.
Yeah.
Yeah, it tried to set them apart in this third category.
Right.
I mean, basically it's a world in which there is no most high God that's an absolute creator
of all things.
Right.
Because once you have that, then you're then who you are and what you are exists in relation
to him.
And that's how it is.
That's how it is.
Yeah.
So, but so there's no third category.
to get by everything just to even see we also
to take into account the fact that we've talked about this in terms of atonement, right,
that evil that sin these things in the world leave a stain, a taint, a residue in the world.
And that that taint and stain is an existential reality in the sense that we
the kid actually experience it.
Right, I think most people have had the experience.
experience of walking into a place.
There's nothing visually wrong with it, right?
Just a house that looks like any other house or building looks like any other building.
But having the firm impression that there's something wrong there and they should leave.
Yeah.
Right.
And and if you ask the person who's that, well, what exactly isn't point to the thing in this room that is wrong or that is bad or that you're running away from or what it is,
They can't there's not some
thing, right? Yeah, that you could point to. Yeah, I like I remember I remember when I my first trip to
to Lithuania actually in Vilnius, there is a museum that was a Nazi and then KGB headquarters,
you know, for in prison. And there was a room in which they would take people and shoot them in
the back of the head. And I mean, I could tell you like I had a when I walked in the room, I was like,
Oh, this place is bad.
Yeah, yeah, there's, and that's a common, right?
But that's an experience.
It's not of the reason you can't point at it
is our experience goes beyond just the material world,
right, that noetic world that we started.
That's right.
This first staff talking about, right?
Our experience includes that, right?
And so a lot of the things the experiences people have
that are related to ghosts or hauntings
that don't seem clearly demonic.
a lot of them are that. So for example, if you're talking about a place where someone did something
horrible to themselves or someone else, there's a kind of spiritual residue of that.
And the way the church has always responded to that kind of thing is by coming and purifying
and sort of rededicating that place, with holy water, with prayer. That can include,
right if it's a place where
someone did something horrible that can include prayer for that person, right?
As part of the process, if you remember back to the cannons about vampire hunting, right?
Some of our new listeners are like, wait, cannons about vampire hunting?
Yes.
Find that Halloween episode.
Yeah.
I think that was our first Halloween episode maybe.
No, I think it was the second one.
Second, maybe?
Okay.
Yeah.
Yeah, yeah, that's.
So, right, and so that's that's how the Churchist responded to that kind of thing, right, is you purify the place and sort of cleanse it from that and rededicate it and pray for whatever people were involved, right?
And that's not saying that there isn't was no demonic activity involved, right?
So I'm likely if someone did something horrible to themselves or others, for example,
that there were demonic
experience involved in that person getting to that point, right?
But it's not just a case of, oh, there's a demon living in my basement always, right?
Or there's a demon attached to this old coffee can, right?
That our PK meter will detect.
Um, so it's not the
there's a middle category of spirits. It's not even that there's a middle category of things.
It's that sin leaves a stain still, right? And that's something that needs to be purified and
cleansed. It doesn't just go away by people ignoring it. Yeah. Yep. Yep. All right. Well,
we're going to go ahead and take our first break and we'll be right back with the second half
of the Lord of Spirits podcast. Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and Father Stephen
the young will be
back in a moment to take your calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits. Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
How do you explain the sacraments? It's easy to say they're mysteries that we have to take on faith
or on the authority of tradition, but that is not how the early Christians understood them.
them. To them and to
To all ancient people, the idea that physical objects had spiritual power was very intuitive,
whereas modern people tend to find this difficult, bizarre, or even, un-Christian.
This is because we live in an era shaped by secularism, a way of viewing a world that's
incompatible with sacramental thinking.
Because secular ideas are at the heart of our culture, modern people tend to think in
secular ways without realizing it, even the most well-meaning of us.
Now then do we live in but not be of a secular culture?
We need to understand the enchanted, sacramental way that the early Christians viewed the world,
but we also need to understand secularism. What is it really? Where did it come from?
And how does it influence how we think about religion?
Journey to reality, sacramental life in a secular age, breaks down these important issues in
accessible, non-academic language and is an ideal introduction for young readers,
catecuments and seekers, as well as for any Orthodox Christians who want to deepen their
understanding of the sacraments.
Journey to Reality.
Sacramento Life in a Secular Age by Zachary Porcu.
Now available at store.angentfaith.com.
Again, that is store.angentfaith.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits,
the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Hey, welcome back, everybody.
everybody we're talking about demonic activity in the world.
And we just finished up doing a bit of a recap
of some of a wide variety of things related to this
from a lot of our earlier episodes.
And we're gonna actually take a couple calls.
So first we have Alexander calling from San Diego.
So Alexander, welcome to Lord of Spirits podcast.
God bless you.
Are you in San Diego proper or are you in like I'm right on the border?
Yeah, that's right. I'm in North County. I'm on the in San Diego County on the North edge of the proper boundaries of
City of San Diego, but I'm so sorry simplicity. Oh, wow. Yes
so I wanted to follow up on
father Stevens
characterization of the red-
of the body and how one way to think about it was that it was reconstituting
a relationship and so what really sparks my interest there is when the
Sadducees challenge Jesus about the resurrection and they bring an example of
marriage and you know marriage is really tied up with relationships and
everything and they challenge Jesus on that. He does the mo you air for you know
You have nothing else to say, I've been used to this.
They'll be like the angels in heaven.
And I think a lot of people take that versus just
as a negative sense.
Oh, angels aren't married.
I don't know if that's really even maybe what
Jesus means.
I think there's a positive meaning there, maybe.
I think I'm thinking of a song where righteousness and peace
have kissed each other.
It feels like that the virtues and that maybe
that the principalities there, they have a deeper communion
that's maybe closer to maybe kind
of an end goal of marriage in the first place.
I don't know how to...
I wanted to comment on how Father Stephen's characterization of the resurrection of the body relates to what Jesus teaches there.
That's all you, Father.
Okay. You don't want to try and get home, actually.
I don't know. I mean, it's interesting to me how much of this thing that you said at Pazofas has legs.
Yeah, usually people forget the stuff. I said no.
Um, yeah, no.
So I'm glad it's got people think because that was again the purpose.
It's a way out.
I'm glad you said it the way you did because a lot of people didn't understand that.
It's a way of.
Yeah.
It's not claiming to be like, this is it, right?
But so what what Christ actually says there is he says in the resurrection people are neither
married nor given in marriage, right?
which would be married would be the male version.
given in marriage would be the woman, right?
But married is also passive.
Yeah, because you have to remember
these are all arranged marriages, right?
So what Jesus is literally saying there is
marriages are not contracted in heaven.
He's not saying, oh you and your wife
are gonna completely forget each other in heaven.
Like you're not gonna recognize each other,
you're not gonna remember any of that time
You spent together.
that love you had for each other is going to be gone, right?
You're not going to remember who your kids were.
Yeah, it might be, I think sometimes, sometimes think maybe it'd be better to translate as there
won't be weddings in heaven, something to get effect, weddings in the life of the age to
come.
Yes.
And see, the point that he was making to the Sadducees is that the reason the Sadducees,
this argument is a species of that.
The reason the Sadducees thought the idea of the bodily resurrection was dumb was
they they heard it as oh
Sometime in the future we're all gonna come back to life and live in the world the way it is now
Right, that's what the Sadducees were rejecting and so
So the Sadducees come to Jesus with this argument against the resurrection.
saying, okay, well, you know,
lever at marriage, this one woman ends up getting married to, you know,
one bride for seven brothers.
Thank you.
All eight of them are now alive again in the world, right?
Right.
Who's wife is she going to be?
Who is it going to be?
And in this context, we're talking about,
who is it going to be lawful for them to have sex with her?
Right. Right. And whose, whose ears will the children be? Because remember, that was the
purpose of leverant marriage. Yep. Right. You, you have a child with the brother and that
brother is considered to be the eldest brother's child and inherits. Right. And so they're
saying, see here, like, yeah, that doesn't work. And so Jesus is saying to them, like, are
you dumb. Basically, you know, that's what the you neither understand.
right? The power we got to our right, like you don't get it, right? Like that's not what the
resurrection is about, right? The the the the resurrection that he compares the resurrected state
to us being like the angels. Yeah, that's in the right 20. The resurrection is not just
this life we have now we come back to it and it goes on forever.
And I'm like writing books and doing podcasts and and drinking Pepsi Max and
Right, just doing it forever.
And the Pepsi Max is just always fresh now.
You know, there's a big line.
You know, this reminds me though that in his commentary on this, although he's as we know,
St. Theophilact of Oakward is basically the Clifnose to Christosdom.
He, not on this passage, but where the rich young ruler comes to Jesus and says,
and says what must they do to inherit internal life?
know, he, the way he interprets that exchange is that the rich young ruler, what he wanted
was the life that he had now forever. Right. So that's the same idea that you were just
talking about.
To be rich. Yeah. Yeah. Exactly. That the, that the resurrection is basically just like
this, but it, but you don't die. You don't get sick or whatever. Right. Yeah. And it's
not. This is a higher thing. And so in the resurrection, Christ is saying, we're not going to be worried
about inheritance rights because why would you if nobody?
We're not going to be concerned about procreation.
We're not going to be concerned about all that stuff is stuff we're concerned about in this
world now, in this time, in this age.
And God has given us commandments governing that.
But the age to come is the age to come.
And things are going to be transformed.
But it seems to me kind of preposterous to suggest that we're just all going to have amnesia.
You know, and you know, you'll be there and your sons and daughters will be there and your wife will be there
But like you won't remember each other and you'll just have the same kind of generic love for each other that you have for everybody
Right and
right
That yeah, and that
You know that that may be that kind of idea of heaven and of the world to come right which get used there changeably
It's probably seepage from the beatific vision, which is toxic sludge from playtobrain, sort
of like, you know, that somehow all of those things were bad, right?
That here's an example of playtobrain related to this.
Let your wife more than you love her.
everyone else is somehow wrong. Yeah. It's somehow selfish or prejudice and wrong, right?
If you have a wife, bold statement I'm about to make, you should love your wife more than
you love any other woman in the world. I don't think that's a bizarre statement, right?
or shouldn't be.
And you have a responsibility for love and support and things to your family
To your parish community that you don't have to everyone in the world and
Trying to pretend that just oh, I love the whole world and everyone in it is number one nonsense
Number two kind of gross, but
But number three it reduces love into something very banal
All.
It gives me a right.
The love I share with my wife is love that's made up of a lot of experiences good and bad that we've shared together.
And the memories of those experiences, right?
That's part of that love.
Right? And again, to change that love into some kind of banal, if you wanted that for some reason, or if you thought morality required it for some Plato-Brayed reason,
would require us to just forget all that.
I just not remember.
Yep.
And then that defeats the point of the bodily resurrection, because then I'm not
me anymore.
The me that rises from the dead.
If the me that rises from the dead doesn't love my wife, it's not me.
It doesn't love my mother and my father, it's not me.
Does it know who my sisters are? It's not me.
it's generic human being number one zero three seven eight nine five five.
Who I guess if you believe the B. A. T. F. A.
vision can go stare at the orb for eternity.
But that's not Christian eschatology.
It's probably just give out your serial number like that father.
I know.
Well, it's it a barcode on the back of my neck.
So I mean, anybody can just edit it and then want to.
Is that clarified things there for you?
that red answer your questions.
Andy, I guess.
Yeah, that's that.
I was thinking it was something like that.
That that Jesus was referring to just the very worldly view
of marriage in terms of, you know, inheritance rights
and it arranged marriage and everything like that.
Is there something to what I earlier suggested though
that like being like the angels
is like a very positive statement
where the angels that it's surrounded God
are like the different principalities
and the virtues and everything.
they're sort of an interpenet.
and interpenned getting nature to them.
So like all of it's like kind of what you hear about.
And that's right, we're all that the virtues are kind of
wedded to other ones.
It's key.
You can't really practice a virtue and isolation.
They kind of they all kind of go together.
Is there something kind of to that and like why?
And like that relating to marriage or is that a stretch?
I would say, I mean, like,
yeah, metaphorically, right?
But like marriage as marriage is,
is frankly.
in the ancient world is about reproduction number one.
Not that it's only about that,
but like for instance, when St. John Damascus
talking about angels, he says that they do not have marriage
because they don't reproduce, right?
So he says that, but yes, in terms of love
and all that, like what you were just describing, sure.
Sure, but I don't think that's what Jesus means
because he went from saying
you know, they're not married and given in marriage, but are like the angels.
You know, so so it wouldn't it wouldn't make sense to say, they're not married and given marriage,
but but they're actually like this other kind of marriage instead. You know, no, it's like the
angels is that the life of the age to come is not like this life. It's quite different.
Right. But I think there's something to what you're saying in terms of the angels and the virtues,
Right.
But so there are there's more than one path to holiness.
Indeed.
Right. Marriage is one of those.
Right. But it's a path to holiness in this life and this age.
Right. And the angels are also holy.
Right. And I think this is connected to why monastics are said to live the angelic life.
Right, I don't think that's unrelated to the celibacy issue.
I think those are connected, right?
They're pursuing a path to holiness that is more similar to the path to angelic holiness
than the path of marriages, but those paths have the same destination.
Yeah.
Over.
All right.
Right.
If that makes sense.
Yeah.
All right.
Thank you very much for calling Alexander.
and take another couple calls.
You know the whole like loving everyone and everything you could I was watching this I won't name it because I don't remember the name it had some
pretentious title I was watching this post apocalyptic TV show and
It was actually the most wholesome apocalyptic TV show in history like there's only one bad person who survived the apocalypse like oh, that's nice
Yeah, like everyone else was just nice and like friendly
But then I was like, well, this is kind of an interesting show.
But then like right at the end of the show, like the big...
character gives this like monologue. And he says, and I quote,
maybe if we learn to live with nature, she can teach us how to live
with each other. And like I threw up in my mouth a little bit, it
was just like, you went through the whole thing. Like you
ruined the whole show. Oh man. Okay, let's take another couple
colors. The the the the call board is actually lighting up.
People are interested in nights.
So we've got Timothy.
So Timothy, welcome to Laura Spierz podcast.
Hi, can you hear me?
We can hear you.
What's going on, Timothy?
So well before I became more to the off
after I've left the Catholic faith
and was just meandering through life.
I moved into an apartment and everything was fine at first.
And I started noticing knocks and balls and things like that.
And my landlord's son lived there and lived there for years.
And I, you know, we became friends because we're both kind of techy and
gamey.
We love gaming and tech.
And I was just expressing to him the things I noticed.
And he said, oh, yeah, there was a guy that died here.
And he was dead for days, maybe a week or more before he was found.
And I thought, OK.
And he said, yeah, I noticed the same kind of things.
It's just part of what goes on here.
And I'm thinking, huh, maybe this is proof of God.
Maybe this is proof of the spiritual life.
And again, keep in mind, this is just me, me,
and me, between faiths.
And oh, gosh, I was thinking, if I could prove this
in the spiritual world, then I got a reason to believe in God,
right?
So there's the draw to me.
And so I start calling out this thing.
And, you know, if you exist, show me yourself.
Prove you exist.
And I'm doing all of this like an ignorance of anything,
just not knowing, just knowing that, like,
I want proof of the afterlife.
I'll just come late in one night.
I'm laying in bed and I had a window with a street light
outside so there was some slight light that came through.
and it was always time I've always seen the world.
And I'm laying there and I get this chill and I look up and the entire room goes pitch
black.
Like there was no light.
There was nothing coming through the window.
There was nothing.
And then this image I saw like inches from my face and I don't know how to explain it
except it was a demon.
And I started praying harder than I've ever prayed.
It profoundly altered my view of what I was doing, right?
And after I started printing, I never, never ever, again,
challenged it, never ever again, asked it to show itself.
And I didn't see that again, but what I saw was the most insidious space
I've ever seen in my life.
I have never been more scared.
And I do know.
that psychologically there's the fulfillment of self-propheties or whatever they call it,
where you think something's going to happen and it happens.
And so I'm not sure if this was something that was self-made or something that I actually
saw, and that's the question I have.
What do you think?
Well, I mean, I don't know what it's like to be you, anymore than I know what it's
like to be a bat.
I mean I would say to me...
right? Like the point of experiences like that, if God permits it, whether it's
some kind of psychological experience or, you know, contact with a demonic spirit or whatever,
the point of all of that is repentance. Like the point is to come away from that
either convert, you know, converting returning to God, you know, increasing your faithfulness,
whatever it might be right?
the question is what should do with it, not so much what was it? It's what do I do with this?
Right, I don't know, Father, what do you think?
Well, I mean, let's hone in on what the question is you're asking.
Like, did this really happen? Well, did it happen or was it it?
Well, of course it happened. It's an experience you really had.
Right?
So I mean, when you say really
happened to me, if you had tried
to touch the face, it would have
been solid, right? Like I mean,
what do you mean by really?
So it was pitch black and then
this image was there.
It was it wasn't lit.
It was just visible on the
and I still remember six inches
from my face on the right
side. I had to turn my head
to see it. It was almost
like it was at the side of my
bed. Right. But so that's an
But so that's actually...
you really have, but the question is, what does real mean? Like it was material?
I'm saying that's what this is. Right. So my point is obviously it's real. You really
had that experience. It really happened to you. Right. And it's not the kind of, it's not
the kind of thing that you could reach out and touch. Right. I didn't have to touch it.
Right, but you see what I'm saying, right?
Like we're not saying this is a
but
material thing, right? Like it's not a question like, is the book really on the dining room table, right?
Like where you can go and check? And the book is there or not, right? And so it's not that kind of issue, right?
Well, when we're talking about any kind of spiritual experience, real means you really had the experience and it was meaningful to you.
And it sounds like you definitely really had this experience and it was definitely really
meaningful to you. Yeah. I think I'm more
pronounced. Yeah. Okay. There you go. But so it's like, it's like me asking, you
know, did I really fall in love with my wife on the day I fell in love with my
wife? Right? What does really mean in that case? Right? Like I had the experience of
falling in love with her. So yes, I really did. Right? Yep. Yep.
Alright, well thank you very much for calling Timothy. God bless you.
All right, we're going to take one more call and then we're going to move on.
So our next caller for this half is Daniel who at least his phone says he's calling from Texas.
So Daniel, welcome to the Lord of Spirits podcast.
How you thought his bless?
God bless you.
Are you indeed in Texas?
I am indeed in Texas.
Texas is a big step.
It is big.
Yes, I'm in Plano.
I go to think Java and Alan with the photos.
Okay.
We know father photo
that close horse. Yeah. So what's on your mind, Daniel? I had kind of a monster
manual question. I was relisting to those episodes and one kind of major
monster group at least in my head that was excluded were ghouls and I was
thinking like these seem to have kind of a connection to like you know like
that sort of werewolf hide.
idea where they're eating, you know, they're kind of cannibalistic, at least if they're
human. And maybe to sort of the, I guess the Greek version of the vampire does some
eating too, you know, more than drinking blood. So I was wondering like, is this kind of,
you know, another reflection of like what an effulom is, is this some kind of demon?
like, what's going on?
Yeah, I mean, Google.
So, Google actually...
fun fact, ghouls from Arabic. So it doesn't appear in English until 18th century. Yeah, yeah, yeah.
So, but I mean, so the concept within Arabic folklore, fairy tales, whatever, is these are,
yeah, as you said, they're they hang on a graveyard as they eat human flesh. So you've got that
kind of cannibalistic imagery. So I mean, yeah, it's
Instapating in the same kind of continuum, as you know, you mentioned the Greek vampire,
the vrykola cuss, that's one you can try on at parties, you know, tell people, so if
you heard of the vrykola cuss and then they'll have, they won't have heard of it, unless
they're Greek and then they'll probably know more about it than you.
You know, it's the same kind of thing as that as, you know, giants, you know, there's,
actually there's an old English word or orcneas, which is where the word orc comes from.
And that's again, sort of...
eating or corpse eating idea and Latin. There's the orcas, which is actually where the
Old English orcneas comes from against sort of flesh eating, although it's fun, like the Latin
orcas is even also like another name for the Hellmouth, but you can see where the how that
would be related. So yeah, it's this kind of being. In most of the literature, it's depicted
in a very kind of fleshy way, right?
So...
I mean, I would like if I'm going to try to kind of, if I'm going to say, okay, this
thing exists in the real world, what it would actually is that I would say that this is,
these are demonized humans, you know, is the way that I would understand them.
Okay.
But again, you know, you're talking about like our image comes from literature for these
things.
Right.
So, you know, you don't necessarily take every single thing in the story in the most literal
possible way, especially since these are not.
These stories are not to be taken literally that's not their their nature at all. So yeah does that that makes sense? Yeah, I
don't know father do you have anything Goulish you wanted to add? I just I just want to say that there's an important disambiguation here that George
Romero style zombies are in fact ghouls not zombies. Oh, excuse me. Serpent in the rainbow that zombies. Those are in fact ghouls. And the
Very cool.
are underrated. Thank you very much for calling Daniel.
Thank you. Say hi to Father Fogious for us.
I will. Great. Great. All right. So is the Groovy Gooleys just totally forgotten media now?
It is for me. I don't think I ever even knew of it or heard of it.
So there's this show, the Groovy Gooleys and friends.
The main the main bit was kind of an anthology. The main bit was the Groovy Gooleys themselves,
who are sort of your universe.
But Goofy and like hip for the late years in early 70s.
I just looked them out. I do recognize this imagery.
But they also they had these sort of sub shows that were like bizarre renditions of like
other recently canceled TV shows like an animated Gilligan's planet that was like the Gilligan's eyes.
Oh, yeah, I remember that was a that was a thing a lot in 1970s cartoons.
Yes, and mush that was like mash but it was dogs
Wow. Wow. And that I'm just looking this up now. There were only 16 episodes of this show and it ran from 1970 to 72.
You know who has them all on DVD? I'll bet you do this guy. Thanks to my wife actually she got them on.
We also have the complete series of Land of the Lost so be jealous. Oh, there you go.
So all right, well, um.
Hey, let's talk about thoughts again. This is another one we get a lot of like
You know, yeah questions about like wait what what
So as as promised in the first half
We're gonna go a little deeper that we talked about how spirits including demons existed the world of thoughts
Right, uh, THOUGHTS
Thank you if you know you know
um
Um, the, uh, what, and what, what that means, right?
So we're going to get a little more into what that means.
And this is going to be pulling from some other old episodes that you may or may not have
listened to and may or may not remember, uh, and try and pull some things together.
And so what are we talking about when we're talking about the world of thoughts and thoughts
in general, right?
As we've talked about, thoughts are not...
We tend to, as contemporary people, think about the mind as the brain, like the organ
the brain.
And since it's in our skull, we think about it as sort of like a computer in a box, right?
And it sort of generates thoughts in there.
And we have this, most of us, not everyone.
This is fascinating to me.
But I've never actually
We met one of these people, but there are people who do not have an intermonologue.
Yeah.
But, I mean, a lot of people.
This isn't like a 1% thing.
This is like a 20% thing of people.
But, you know, we have this idea that we're sort of generating thoughts in this box.
And so, you'll see questions like in Christian circles, can demons or can the devil, can they
hear your thoughts or read your thoughts?
course, within fiction.
science fiction in particular and superhero fiction, right?
Telepathy being able to read other people's thoughts.
And you know, that means you could read the little balloon over their head, right?
Eight of us.
What they're thinking to themselves, right?
Are you telling me that counselor Troy and Commander Riker couldn't actually talk
to each other telepathically?
No, because she was only half beta zoid and so could only get thoughts and emotions.
she couldn't get like actually in reading like her.
mother, low, exana could man the voice of the computer turn in your fan club cards,
sir. No, no, no, there's episodes like when, when, when she shows up for the first
time in the enterprise and she encounters Riker and this is what their anxiety thing.
Free beard. Like fate, you hear the little I'm thinking, I'm thinking out loud sound.
Like they forgot that I got swept under the rug later.
Like their relationship.
All right.
Yeah. I'm just saying that's like in the first episode and counter at far point. There's
lots of weird things in the first episode encounter at far point. It is kind of a weird
episode. It would love for the beard. All right. So. But so that's that's how we think about
it. Right. Yes. That's the thought. Right. Right. And this is a completely different
paradigm than anyone in the ancient world had.
or that Christians had for most of Christian history about what thoughts are, what the mind is,
how it works, right? The fact that we think brain right off the bat, right, should tip you off
that this isn't how they thought about thoughts, right? And so if we think a little more,
if we think a little phenomenologically, we've said this before the show, we don't really have
the experience of generating a thought.
In the sense that like if you write a sentence, if I'm sitting in front of my computer and
I type out a sentence or if I'm sitting with a piece of paper and a pen, I know Gene
Alphay, you don't know what I'm talking about.
But and I'm going to write a sentence, right?
I have to formulate the sentence, right?
And I think about what word I'm going to use next and I, we don't have that experience
with a thought.
shows up in our heads sort of fully for.
Yeah, which I would like to disinviguate a little bit everybody because I know this is where people get tripped up
They're like no wait. I've thought about things like I came up with he is right right now
We've had the experience of connecting thoughts together right
But thoughts that are just sort of present themselves to our brain holy formed and sometimes we go where did that come from?
Yeah
Yes, right or that's horrible why
I'm thinking that right or if you're like me, it's already come out of your mouth and you've said it before you realize
And people are looking at you weird or they're used to you and they just go father's to
So the way the way this was understood by ancient people and
Throughout Christian history is that the news the mind is not referring to the brain
Which is in a box of some kind, but the mind itself is sort of like a sensory organ
Yeah, it like your eyes are your ears, right? Yeah, it things come in
Right, it's a way the things come in in the same way that you know if my eyes are open
And I'm looking past my microphone at my church office, right? I'm not choosing
To see my wall calendar my wall calendars just there right in my field vision
You can look at it.
But you're right. I can focus on it. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. I can focus on my wall calendar where I can turn in focus on an icon on the wall
Or I can turn in focus on the door, right?
But if I've just generally looking straightforward all of those things are in my field division. I'm not choosing to see them. Yeah
Right, I don't have the experience of like constructing this image of the office
Right, just I open my eyes. That's what presents itself to me. Okay. Yep. Yep
And so thoughts are similar, but for the mind, right?
So the mind perceives a thought.
Right? A thought comes in through the mind.
Right? And we have then a point of attention that could be directed.
We can direct our attention to a particular thought and dwell on it, connect it to other thoughts and ideas.
we can try to expel a thought we tried to focus on something else.
Right? Because we don't like the thought that's presenting itself or the experience that's presenting itself.
But the thoughts show up. Right? And this is why you'll see the fathers referring to the news as the eyes of the heart or the eyes of the soul.
Right? Because that's the comparison that it's like your eye. Right?
Right. But with thoughts. Now, as Father Andrew said, we need to disampig you.
here between a thought and an idea. Okay, between a thought and an idea because
sometimes people when they're trying to understand what we mean by this will
say, well, no, I have had the experience of generating a thought and then what
they describe to us is putting together an idea. Right. Right. Using thoughts to
construct an idea. Okay. So we're going to disambiguate what the difference is
here between thoughts and ideas.
I would maybe even also add in
thing king, which is a sort of active engagement
with the thought.
Right.
Thinking is what's involved in the formulation of ideas.
Yeah.
Right.
I'm going from thought to idea.
I mean, part of it is, like this,
now we're using modern English words,
but we're describing things that there are distinct ways
of speaking about in the church fathers for sure.
but I don't know, does ancient Greek...
philosophy make these kinds of distinctions as well.
Yes.
OK, so yeah, part of it is that we've lost, we've kind of
conflated everything having to do with our minds into this
one thing that we call thoughts or thinking.
Right.
Like for, yeah, fundamental, again, fundamentally different view
of what the mind is and how it works.
Yeah.
Right.
They're sort of processing data, right?
Or churning, right?
Lord that it's us.
narrating our life to ourselves, right? Or if you're one of those 80% with the intermodal
lock. But so thoughts just appeared on our mind unbidden. We've all had this experience, right?
Sometimes it's very inopportune times, right? And it's not something that most of us untrained as we are,
Right, uh, it can't control. Right. Give a stopper thought.
coming into our head. When we're sitting right, you know, we think of something funny and
laugh at it in appropriate time. We think of something simple. I never do that.
What a blot of out of our brain. Well, I always speak for myself. So that was the royal
We are not I was I always I always use the editorial we yeah
So, that's thoughts, right?
Thoughts just sort of show up, right?
Whereas ideas are formed, right?
Ideas are something we come up with.
We put together an idea.
We engage in the process of thinking about those thoughts
that have come into our mind and put them together
and construct ideas, right?
and those ideas that we can struct.
are tools. We've talked about this on the show before too. They're tools in that there's something we use to do something
Right. They're helpful to us in some way. The idea is
Right.
But ideas are not spirits because they don't have agency. Ideas don't do things. Right. Right. Like
like the idea of
Well, what, right.
Uh, any one of my books, right?
Religion of the Apostles, right?
Take one of my books.
That is a set of ideas, right?
That I put together, right?
Over time.
I published.
If you destroyed every copy,
and I die, right?
And everyone who remembers reading it dies, okay?
Those ideas will escape.
essentially cease to exist.
In the sense that that book will never come together exactly the same and spare me the
Million chimpanzees with typewriters, right?
I
Mean it used to be said that if you put a million chimpanzees with a million typewriters
They would eventually produce the works of William Shakespeare
But we have been running an experiment since the mid 1990s
That's called the internet and we know that that is not true. Yes
Because there's more than a million chimpanzees banging on cheese.
That's right.
So, it's gone.
Those ideas are gone.
But the thoughts, the impressions, the data, the things that I built into those ideas are
not gone.
And someone could construct something similar, somewhere else.
But the idea does that sort of have its own existence.
Right. The book does not have any existence beyond the memories of people who have read
it and the copies of the book. There's no eternal existence of any of my books. Sorry,
Plato, ideas are not eternal. Oh, it's our first sorry Plato for the night. Right.
so
So ideas they don't have agency they can't do things right isms can't do things
People do things
people use ideas
As tools to do those things
Right, but the ideas themselves don't do anything
Okay, this is this is the basic problem
with most atheist arguments against religion.
Most atheist arguments for your average internet atheists will argue that quote unquote religion does things.
Yeah.
Or quote unquote Christianity does things.
Right.
Religion has caused all the wars in the world.
Really a set of ideas.
How did a set of ideas do that?
Right? No, people did that. Right.
For the use that you did that. But you can see, look at America before the Civil War,
there were people using ideas about the Bible to support slavery and using ideas about
the Bible to call for the abolition of slavery at the same time. Indeed.
basically the same culture.
So those ideas that they formed were tools, right?
The ideas couldn't do anything.
And see, this is the thing.
When atheists say religion does blah, blah, blah, what they really mean is that God does it.
Yeah. Yeah, but.
And they don't like it and they don't like God and they're angry at him, but they don't want to admit that he exists.
And so they have to say religion does it.
even though it's preposterous to think that a set of disembodied ideas does things.
So, sorry, if he is.
But so, ideas and thoughts are not the same.
But so, here's an analogy.
Because I know this is tricky.
I know we're losing some people.
So, think of thoughts as sense impressions.
So, we could compare the news.
The mind is a sensory organ to your eye, to vision.
sensory organ.
right? So thoughts that are like the visual data that just floods in through your eyes when your
eyes are open right? Yeah. So there's just visual data. Yeah. All of us have had the experience of
looking out a window or looking across the room and seeing something and not knowing what it is.
Right? That happens to me more and more as my eyes age. Yeah.
We're
We're receiving visual data.
We're like, what's that?
Right?
Like, what's that over there on the floor?
Or what's that outside the window on the lawn?
Right?
And we try to frame, right?
Like what, you know, and resolve it into what it is.
We're getting accurate sensory data.
The color of the shape, all of that is accurate.
It's coming in our eyes, right?
But we don't know what it is, right?
So that's like thoughts.
Ideas are like when we resolve, we focus in on it and say, oh, right?
That's, you know, another dog toy that my dogs have torn up.
That's why that's a misshapen blob now.
Right?
Lay over there on the floor.
That's an idea.
Right?
Now, that idea could be wrong.
I might be wrong about what that is over there on the floor, and I can go and look at
you
C, oh, am I right?
I'm like, oh, it's not that.
It's actually this other thing.
Right?
But the sensory data I was getting was accurate.
So thoughts come into our head, and then we resolve those thoughts into ideas.
Yeah.
Right.
And the ideas we resolve them into are things that are useful for us.
So for example, when I've identified what I think the thing is, oh well, it's just that.
Now I don't have to worry about it.
I don't have to get up and go over there and pick it up. I know what it is. Right? That's useful to me because I'm lazy.
Right? Or I've lost something, I'm trying to find it and then I see it. There it is. Right?
But the idea is like another level of abstraction from reality that could be wrong.
And that's because when we go from just a thought
to an idea, when we go from just visual data to an image,
to resolving an image, our own subjectivity
enters into it.
Our own subjectivity, our own past experiences,
help us recognize things when we see something similar.
If you see some object you've literally never seen before,
Right, you're gonna be trying to...
come up with some idea of what it is, whereas someone who has seen that object before will
see it go, oh, that's a blank, right?
Again, that might be a false assumption.
It might look like something they've seen before, but not be that same thing, right?
Because that's their subjectivity, and it's into it.
Some completely new object might kind of resemble two different objects, and people familiar
with either of them will both think that that's the object they're familiar with.
Thank you.
either. And so this is this is the kind of thing that happens with ideas. So when we talk about ideas,
we categorize them in different ways. Right. So one of them is distinguishing good ideas from bad
ideas. If you used to watch Animaniacs, you may be familiar with good idea, bad idea. Yeah. Right.
But there
we're talking about ideas of this very utilitarian way as tools, right? So we're saying, you know,
it was a good idea for me to stop on the way home and get some milk because we were out,
right? Meaning that worked out well, right? What I did worked out well. A bad idea would
be, it was a bad idea to stop and get milk on the way home because it turned out we had
three gallons in the fridge.
that were, you know, not ready to expire. Right. See, at my house, there's six gallons in the fridge.
Okay. But, you know, do you like the kids have any? Pretty much every week. Yeah, I know.
I apparently drink two gallons a week myself, as I discovered one time when I was home without
everybody else. That's not bad, because my parents famously had to limit me to half a gallon a day as
a kid. There you go. So I guess I was at three and a half a week.
but yeah, there you go.
There you go.
But I was a growing boy.
So,
Amen.
With a Titanic bone structure.
He's a talk about the ship people.
Yeah, it's now sinking fast.
But anyway, it's not 50.
So,
but we could also talk about good ideas and evil ideas.
Right
So I drive across town in my town. I see that there are a lot of homeless people in my town.
Right. Based on what I saw, right, and what I experienced, I come up with this idea.
Someone needs to do something to help these people. Right. We need to build a homeless shelter. We need to help them find jobs. Right.
whatever we need to help
people, right? We say that's a good idea in that sense. Or I go and I have the same experience,
I see it when I say we need to round these people up and execute them all. That idea. That would
be an evil idea. Not a bad idea, an evil idea, right? This isn't a utilitarian thing.
Evil as in the fluids of the devil. Yes. Yes. I for one follow the Judeo-Christian ethic of
of thou shalt not murder, but, uh...
So, right, so that is an evil idea.
It might be a utilitarian sense, easier to accomplish.
Right?
It might be easier to exterminate all of the poor people than to lift them out of poverty
by providing them with opportunity.
That doesn't make it good.
All right, the good option.
Because we understand morality.
It's still that's an evil thing to do.
So there could be good and evil ideas,
but that's because these ideas are constructed.
So when it comes to thoughts,
we can't control what thoughts
and are our brain anymore than when you open your eyes,
you can control what you see in front of you.
Someone can hold up something.
obscene in front of you and you're going to see it, whether you want to or not.
Right?
You could make the mistake of opening that message I send you and seeing the meme and being
horrified, right?
And you can't unsee it now, right?
But you don't get to choose, right?
Once it's before your eyes, it's before your eyes, right?
And the same kind of thing is true with thoughts.
Thoughts will enter your head, right?
That you didn't want to enter your head and you desperately want to get out of your head.
didn't come from you that came in from outside just like
something you see. But what we can control is what thoughts we allow to form ideas and
what ideas we allow those thoughts to form. And then after that, what ideas we choose to
act on. So we've used the metaphor before on the show. And this is us trying to be more
concrete about it. The metaphor on the show of thoughts being like seeds and you control
which ones you allow to take root.
and grow, that taking root and grow is forming into ideas.
Yeah. Right. And what ideas, right?
They are, they are allowed to form.
So thoughts can be accepted and rejected.
You could have a thought and not allow it
to become an idea.
You could reject a thought.
Yeah. Right.
I think by focusing on other things.
I think it's the, I used to use the describes thoughts
or like airplanes going overhead and you're on airport.
You don't...
don't have to direct all of them to land.
Yeah.
Right.
And part of that is choosing which ones we focus on.
Yeah.
Right.
But then even the thoughts that come in
and that we allow to form ideas, the thoughts
that we then think about that we dwell on, right?
We have control of what kind of ideas those produce, right?
produce, right? For example, you meet a person.
Right from whatever impressions you get
spiritually and materially from what they say from how they present as those were that I talk you get the impression this is a bad person
Right, this is not a good person
That's the impression you have that's the thought that comes into your head right
You can formulate that thought into different ideas right ideas like I should pray for this person
I should try to
help this person. I need to talk to this person about what they're doing because
they don't realize how harmful it is. Right? Or it can be, this is a bad person.
Right? This person should be canceled. This person should be shunned. I should
verbally abuse this person. I should cut this person off. I should go and
warn everyone and talk about the detail what a bad person this is. Right? All
All those different ideas can come...
from the same thoughts and the same impressions.
And some of those are good, and some of those are bad,
and some of those are evil.
And we have control over that
because at that point, we're at this sort of processing phase.
And so,
this is where the idea of, right,
A thought becomes a sinful thought when that thought leads you to sin.
Right. Right.
And we mean that metaphorically. The thought can't cause you to sin.
Right. But you can develop that thought into a sinful idea.
Or not. Right. So a thought, right.
That that isn't so let's take a thought. Right.
Right.
You are in church, right?
You have a beautiful spiritual experience in liturgy that morning.
Okay?
And you thought, that was a beautiful experience.
I felt very close to God, right?
You can take that as good as that.
It doesn't seem to be anything bad or evil about that, right?
Right, but if you go and brag about it because it's you to have pride.
if it causes you to belittle other people, right?
If the next week you don't have that experience
and you sort of start to blame the noisy kid in the back row
and you go and you say, you know, mean things to the parents,
because you know, they ruined your experience the next week, right?
All of those are a thought that was, you know, seemingly good,
that you have allowed to turn into an idea that is not.
Right.
Yeah.
and
My source that can be true.
Right?
There are people who have seen horrible things.
There are accounts of saints who have seen prostitutes.
Right?
And have wept for them.
And prayed for them.
Right?
And a lot of men when they see prostitutes have different ideas that they form in their
heads.
Right?
Yeah.
right it's not the thoughts themselves
Right. It's what we do with them. And hopefully, that's a little more concrete.
And the place where we really work on this is prayer.
Hmm. Because prayer is the place.
One of the things prayer does for us.
So there are a lot of them. But one of the things prayer does for us is help us train our mind,
train our news, right?
To make it more acute and more responsive, right?
Um, to not be dulled.
Right? Sometimes you've got to clean your ears out and get the wax out. Right? Sometimes
you need glasses to correct your eyes. Right? Well, prayer sort of does this for our spiritual
vision. Right? And so we've talked about it on the show before how the Jesus prayer is
referred to as the prayer of a single thought because you're training your brain to just
focus on one thought, to shut out the whole other cavalcade of thoughts. It's like a
and you're shutting it all out to just
hear one voice, right, or one sound, right, and ignore everything else. Women with lots of children
probably already have this ability when it comes to hearing. But, right, learning how to focus our
mind in that way, right, and put out the other thoughts, right, because this is when people are trying,
how many times have you tried to sit down and pray and you go through a whole page in a prayer book
Okay, you have no idea what you read.
Yeah.
And or I mean, that even happens like if you're reading a book, you know, like, wait,
how did I just read?
Yeah.
Right.
Because you're having all these other thoughts.
And in prayer, it doesn't have to be like evil thoughts.
Not just any thought.
Yeah.
Hey, did you lock your car doors?
Right.
I'm hungry.
You sure though?
My coffee is getting cold.
Yeah.
And just a cavalcade of the what was that noise?
What was that other noise?
And you know, so that...
training to be able to focus on a single thought. The ultimate goal is what is called by father's
wordless prayer, right? Which I'm not claiming to have experienced, Father Andrew can speak for
himself. I will also not claim that you have experienced it. Yes, there we go. Or that I have.
Right where you're able to get past the thoughts and just sort of directly be in the presence
of God, but the first step to even approaching anything like that is being able to focus on
one thought, right?
Yeah.
To focus on Christ.
And so, I mean, it's trading your news.
One thing that like this is, if you've never had the experience of standing vigil, like
in church, which you know, like for hours and hours and hours and hours, especially like
late at night, which is a monastic practice.
you can sometimes find it in some parishes.
You get to the point where you're so tired and so exhausted that if you then say to your
mind, let's pray, actually, you can almost achieve this just by being exhausted.
Right, which is like, well, sure enough, there's a reason why this practice exists.
You know, like, it's so tired that you're like,
okay, let's pray.
And you don't have the energy to do anything but do that.
Yeah, yeah, so that's one way I'm not saying everybody needs to do that, but it is a thing. I've
experienced it once or twice in my life. Yes, and it's and all these practices are aimed at teaching
you to not think. Yeah. As weird as that sounds. That's not say out saying, oh don't question anything.
Do as we say no, no, no, it's just like learn how to turn it off and just yes, you know, yeah,
and focus. Right, and be deliberate. And as you learn
to focus that you can be more deliberate about the kind of ideas you form in your mind.
Right? And the kind of... And so this is one of the things people don't realize. And it's
on purpose. The Enlightenment did this on purpose. Trying to strip away anything remotely
religious from the philosophers of the past, right? But actual plateness, like...
at the academy. It wasn't just like, oh yeah, we read Plato's stuff and I agree with it.
Right. There was a whole way of life associated with it. Yeah, yeah. Same thing with Aristotle.
And that included various meditation and prayer practices.
Yeah.
That were aimed at, right?
Learning how to think deliberately, right? It had to focus the mind.
Right? Now, obviously this wasn't being, but I mean, this is, this is, when they talk
about the third eye in Eastern religions, right? That's the news. That's what they're
talking about. They're trying to do this. Now, try to do this apart from Christ is dangerous.
Yeah. Not, not a good idea. It's all get out. And I'm not saying you should use their practices
to do this. But that's what they're aimed at, right? The, the, the, the, the, the broad
understanding of the ancient world that you know if you're going to actually think.
right that you got to train your mind to do it. And that's not just memorizing a bunch of logical
fallacies, right, so that you can accuse people of them online and get them wrong every time it's
a circle, you know, or taking advanced symbolic logic courses, it's it's training your mind, your
faculty to actually do it.
Right? Reading Logic Texts.
books is like reading about, like reading a sports playbook or reading a book about chess,
right?
Yeah.
Like you could learn a lot of things.
Yes.
Right.
But, you know, and important things, but at some point you got to play chess, so you got to
play ball or you got to do the thing and you got to practice doing the thing to hone
your ability to do the thing.
And so this is part of what prayer does for us is teach us how to think and how to process the things that we see in the world, both with our material senses and with the eyes of our heart.
Alright, well our first half was about demons and their activity.
Second half about thoughts, you might be thinking, what are these things have to do with each other?
We'll just hang-
on because in the third half believe it or not we're going to bring it all together.
So we're going to take our next break and we'll be right back.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymick and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment to take your
calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
The centuries after the Protestant Reformation brought...
about a radical reinterpretation of the epistles of St. Paul, disconnected from any historical
reality.
The Paul operated during his entire life as a faithful Pharisee within the Roman Jewish
world.
In St. Paul the Pharisee, Jewish Apostle to all nations, Father Stephen D. Young surveyes
Paul's life in writings, interpreting them within the holy tradition of the Orthodox
Church.
This survey is followed by De Young's interpretive translation of St. Paul's Epistles.
which deliberately avoids overly familiar terminology.
By using words and ideas grounded in 1st century Judaism,
DeYoung hopes to unsettle commonly held notions
and help the reader reassess Saint Paul in his historical context.
Available now at store.ancientfaith.com
Again, that is store.ancientfaith.com
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits,
the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question
Call now at 855-237-2346. That's 855-AF radio.
Hey, welcome back everybody.
This episode of Laura Spears Podcast, we're talking about demons.
And we're going to discuss demon possession here in the third half.
But we have a, we're going to take two calls. We're going to take two calls.
So, we have to take three.
Okay, okay, I'll do three.
Okay, that's it everybody just three so if you're in you're in if you're not we have to take 40 no
How orthodox are we have we done I don't think have we ever done 40 calls like one of our life calling shows
I don't think I've read 40. I don't think so we've done 40 speak pipes
Yeah, and I don't think snow. I don't think like yeah, no, I don't think so and a single
I'm the one who puts them together man. We've been in the high 30s
Hey!
Anyway, okay, so first we're gonna take James,
who is calling from Oklahoma, but I don't remember
the rest of the line, but anyways,
James, welcome to the Lord's Pierce podcast.
You've waited so patiently.
Is there a bright golden haze on the meadow?
Thanks for that, Father's bless.
I do have just a, just a couple of questions
about like fashion, because I'm familiar with the Bible,
you know, it's kind of reading it,
before going to orthodoxy as it protested.
And I know like
It says in a Bible, there's all kinds of symbology there.
Dan jumping out of fashion, when it's in the prophecy of the patriarchs to the 12 sons of Israel.
There's also Ogg being the king of fashion.
And recently, I know it's a best-related in Syria to the
and Heights area, which also has a lot of historical connotations.
So I'm kind of wondering what the symbology of that is.
And just another question, maybe in more related to the podcast.
So in regards to, like, I mean, that question is, like, I know it's like, I'm kind of starting
to think about icons kind of like at the same time they kind of maybe reflect something
spiritually of ourselves.
So like...
Like, you know, sometimes like we grow up with certain preconceptions, like for example,
you know, there might be like, for example, like a certain false masculinity, which is incompatible,
like with gentleness, for example.
So when you go to an icon, if you have trouble, you know, kissing the icon, sometimes I'm wondering
is that, is that actually an evil spirit?
In that case.
And just the third question, they'll just kind of put in there.
Going a little bit more mystically,
like the five wounds of Christ on the cross.
Is that, are those related to five books Moses
and is the four gospels is data associated
with the Tetra Maggram, like YHWH
in the Old Testament?
That'll be my questions.
That's all right.
Wow, you really racked them up there.
Okay.
Well, yes, you have three.
Yeah, there you go.
She asked three questions.
I think we'll try to just give short answers.
What is the importance of Bashan, Father Steven?
I mean, obviously, there's a land of aug.
Right.
Yeah.
So Bashan was the place of residence of a giant clan
that of which aug was the chiefed in or the king.
Bashan was also later a center for bail worship.
It's where I'm out here in a minute.
is up there in the Mount Hermann remember is you know,
Haram, Karram, it's the
Kirsten Mountain essentially because it's covered with
pagan shrines, the ancient pagan shrines are still there on
it, right? You can go see them everywhere.
No, that's
the and so it was a center for bail worship later.
And so it was sort of
the homeland of sort of spiritual evil in the north. It represents a lot of
prophetic literature. My favorite reference to it actually is the women of the
northern kingdom of Israel being referred to as the sleek cows of Bashan, which
was related to Bolbal and what he did to cows.
So.
So yeah, but yeah, so that's sort of what what Bashan represents, which is in the modern
day, Golem Heights, which has been rubble for a long time.
Yeah, yeah.
I mean, with regards to the second question, really quickly, like, is it an evil spirit if
you don't want to do a pious thing like kissing an icon?
I will just say keep listening, just keep listening to the rest of this half.
And then you asked a question about numerological symbolism, like five wounds of Christ.
was it?
I'm trying to remember now the existence that you made.
Yeah, five wounds of Christ with,
what was the five things that you were comparing it to?
The tattoo, like with the five of you Christ.
Yeah, and then tetragramatarn and the four gospels.
I mean, all of those things have been used
by the church fathers.
They'll connect that stuff.
But it's not like there's some kind of
absolute inherent magical formulaic numerology going on there.
Like, these are images that are used
in interpreting the scriptures, right?
But it's not...
like there's some sort of secret code that's unlocked by saying, oh, here's a number
four. And here's another number four, you know, that's, and Chris had more than five
ones. Yeah, right. Exactly. He was scourged on his back. He was, right? I mean, yeah.
But it's a teaching tool, right? Exactly. Exactly. To make a connection.
All right. Thank you very much for calling James. There we go. Three for one. We're going to take two more
So our next is Ryan.
and welcome to Laura Spears' podcast.
What's on your mind?
Not much.
You kind of already covered one of my questions
with the caller that had a question about nightmares.
Oh.
I'm a big fan of your buffet, by the way.
Yes, I am as well.
Anyway, good call, Father Steven, good call.
I'm gonna ask about stuff like
Parasome is like sleep walking, people who will just sort of get up and or maybe not even
get up, but those just do something in like they're not awake, right?
But they're also definitely not sleeping normally if there's any kind of spiritual side to
that because people will do some weird things when they're asleep.
Yeah, generally.
Yeah, is there a spiritual side?
sleepwalking and so forth. I mean, yes. I don't I hope not. Oh, you hope that I mean you're
we're we're we're spiritual beings. I can't. Well, no, I know. I know. Yeah. Yeah. But in the sense that
I don't think there's anything, uh, diabolical about it. Percent. No, no, no, not necessarily. Yeah.
Yeah. Right. Um, now there are people who do like violent things or sexually appropriate things.
And that kind of like that then you're in
different territory. Right. Yeah. But, you know, you feel so I got I got to tell a couple
stories now. Okay. Right. Most of this was a result of my untreated sleep
apnea. Now that I have a CPAP machine, most of this has gone away. But even when I was
a kid, I slept walk all the time. I would like go to sleep in my bed and wake up on the couch.
I would wake up wearing a hat.
Uh, just various things like...
that. This advanced to the point that my wife would hear like if I was studying
something in another language before I went to sleep, I would be like speaking Hebrew
or Greek or something in my sleep, but you would think I was possessed.
Nice.
But the most famous one of these, and I don't know if I've mentioned this on the show before,
but at one night in the middle of the night, I said loudly and clearly out of the blue
And she heard it.
I said,
And that's how you kill William Faulkner.
Oh, you've told me this.
Yes, fuck.
And I know there's no context to it, right?
And I didn't remember whatever dream I was having.
So I don't know if I had just like outlined a heist scheme
and said, and that's how you kill William Faulkner.
If I had just murdered William Faulkner
and I was pointing at him and saying,
that's how you kill William Faulkner, I don't know what the context was.
I don't know if it was killing...
his memory. If I had some problem with the sound in the fury that I mean he is dead. Yes.
I was just doing a historical report. Right? I don't know. But so yeah, I had a lot of what might
be called weird sleep behaviors and disturbances, but they were never violent or sexual. Right?
In any way. And so I think that kind of stuff is basically just it's a product of like my sleep
I wasn't sleeping well. It was messing with my brain.
And so my brain wasn't shutting off my motor, yeah, reflexes while I was asleep.
Now if you get into that other territory, right, the violent or sexual territory, then there's
a different problem discussion right there.
Yeah.
Okay.
Well, thank you very much for calling Ryan.
All right.
We're going to take one more caller.
Talker fans.
Yeah.
I'm not a Faulkner fan.
I'll just tell you that right now.
Yeah.
Yes, so we've got Tyler. Tyler will be our final call for the evening.
So make it good. Welcome to Lord of Spirits podcast. Yeah, make it good.
Thank you, fathers. Not long after my grandfather passed within a few weeks,
I was so woken one night by a dark figure in my house.
And in those days, I still suffered from severe Protestant mind and thought that it might have
then some sort of demon or some sort of...
of dark entity and asked Christ to protect me and the dark figure sort of went away into the corner.
But as I approached the church and I learned more about the intermittent state or the intermediate
state, I sometimes wonder if that might have been him visiting me or in some sense. I should
mention that in those days I would often listen to scripture on a tape.
And my question is, is there a way that we can differentiate between dark entities as demonic
or demonized, fully demonized people or our past loved ones who may revisit us or may
revisit places they've been in their life?
Yeah.
I mean, St. John Christophe, business right father, he has a homily where he talks about
Thank you.
What did you counter the spirit of a dead loved one?
Yes.
Yeah.
And I mean, as a common experience that people have.
I mean, as I recall, correct me if I get into this wrong, what he basically says is, it's
supposed to, you know, don't just simply accept it and, you know, whatever, but it's supposed
to lead you to repentance no matter what it is that you experience.
Um, well also also you
treat those experiences based on the fruit thereof. Right, right. What is the outcome?
So the effect that that experience has on your life is to bring you to your repentance,
or to bring you joy or consolation, to bring you closer to God, then by all means embrace
that experience as a good and positive thing. Don't become proud about inner arrogant,
but it's virtually arrogant, but except it's a good thing.
If what that...
that produces in you is fear or unsettling or something else that has the opposite effect
that that disturbs your Christian life, then reject it as demonic.
Because if God has some message He wants to get to you, He could get it to you loud and
clear, right?
And unambiguously.
Yeah.
So.
No hinting required.
that rejecting that, rejecting a potentially positive experience is not going to cheat you
out of anything.
Right?
God will clarify it for you.
Whereas, you know, too quickly embracing experience that may have negative elements can
cause problems down the line.
Yeah.
I see.
Thank you.
Thank you very much for calling Tyler.
All right.
Okay, so we're talking about demonic possession now. Thank you very much everybody who called.
We're gonna just roll on through the rest of this episode and we'll get to you on a
You don't want to open the lines for people who maybe demon possessed.
We're not gonna go full art bell on this. No, no, no. I mean people have been waiting around for
what we're about to discuss so they just announced that they're making it art bell biopic.
Are you serious?
starting to call Geomoddy.
Oh wow, maybe we should do like an M
ST3 K bird.
We'll be fine.
Yes.
Right.
So, here we go.
Demonic possession.
What do demons do?
Right.
As usual, we get to our actual topic in the third half.
So,
the first place where we really see, I mean, obviously, right.
right
the serpent in the garden is demonic activity. We talked about the falls. We talked about that in
another episode. That's right. It involves things we would call demons, but the kind of demonic
activity that we're talking about now, right? Because where we're going with this is what are demons
doing today? Not just a historical survey or a biblical survey, but what are they doing today?
Here in the 21st century. But how we understand that does have its roots in scripture, right? So
So the first place we go is to King Saul.
in first Samuel or first
kingdoms. If you're using that Orthodox
study model where we see Saul
after his sin is this unclean
spirit is sent by God,
detourment and trouble him. Yeah,
when it says that the Holy Spirit,
the Holy Spirit left.
him. Right. Yeah. And God sends this unclean spirit instead to trouble it. Now this is not,
there's a lot of people have a real problem just with what I said already. Right. God sending an
unclean spirit, God sending a demon on Saul. And part of that is because I think people read it
as a punishment like oh he was bad. So God, you know, if I do, if I stand, if I do something that
God's gonna send a demon to torment me. No, it's actually actually it's a kind of
tough love. Yes. So the idea was that the torment of this unclean spirit would drive him to repentance.
Right. Because he was kind of too comfortable before. So help him. And so how much he needs God,
frankly. Yeah. And so this spirit comes to torment him. The this is related to what St. Paul says,
when he's talking about excommunicating someone as sort of the final step of church discipline to
call the repentance, he refers as handing them over to Satan.
Yeah, right. Like this is the idea. The idea is, well, at a certain point, you cut them off
with these. In the hope that they will repent and come back once they see how bad it is to be
sort of on the outside, right? And so, so I'll put on the outside. But rather than that leading him to
repentance leads him to anger, rage, murderous rage against David, the resentment, everything but
But...
patents. Right. When we get to the book of Tobit, we get to a case that of demonic activity
that's starting to look more like what we see in the New Testament. So, Tobit, probably
There are a lot of folks who are listeners who are Protestant friends or who are from a Protestant
an background who may not have read Tobit. You should read it by the way, even if you
like don't regard it as scripture, it's a great story. Yeah. I mean, it is at least a great
piece of second-time literature, right? Even if you object to full canonicity or what have you.
But so in Tobit, so because people haven't read it, we're going to frame this a little more.
So in Tobit there's this problem presented where Tobit's son is going to marry this woman
Sarah problem being there's this demon as modius.
Yeah, she's been engaged a much times before.
Yeah.
And so as we talked about in the marriage episode, marriage proper was basically the consummation
of the mirror.
That's when you were married. That's what he moved for Betroth the Mary. So it's consummated and every time one of these seven men
Had tried to come in and consummate the marriage
As modius had killed them
Yeah
It's a little traumatic. I mean this is yes
This is kind of a scary story in some ways. Yes
Yes, and so you know tobit obviously does not want his son to be the next one
but to be
it is sun or on this journey with the archangel Raphael accompanying them and the archangel
Raphael helps them out and gives them something to do which will there are a couple of problems.
One problem is that Tobin has been struck blind. The other problem is dealing with azmodius
and uh...
st. Rafael
tells them to catch a certain fish
and prepare it in a certain way,
do certain things with it,
burn certain parts of it as an offering.
And then that will take care of the blindness issue
and take care of Asmodius.
A lot of people have problems with this part
because they're like,
what is this weird,
why is the, you know, this archangel giving,
why is it voodoo recipe?
Right?
Like, to do this and, you know,
so this is one of those things.
So.
Certainly of our Protestant friends who are really opposed to seeing a book like Tobit
as being part of the Old Testament, they will do this thing where they go through it and
they try to find everything that they think is ridiculous.
So like this, like this fish thing.
And say, oh look, that's ridiculous.
This can't be part of the Bible.
But I can go on YouTube right now and find some atheists say, oh look, Baylap's donkey
talks to him.
That's ridiculous.
Yeah.
Right.
Axe had floating.
That's ridiculous.
Right.
Is he going to run you around the city naked?
Is he going to see all this weird stuff in the sky?
Literally, he's taking LSD, right?
They say all the same stuff, right?
Now our Protestant friends who make the argument.
about Tobit will be quick to rush to defend the scriptures they view as
canonical against those accusations when an atheist makes them. But then they
make the exact same accusations on the same basis.
Right. Using the same standard of believability
about books that they think should be excluded. That's not weighing with even scales.
Right. Let's think about this which thing for a minute. Do not the profits
in the Old Testament, and angels who come to visit people in the New Testament.
Give them signs with material things, or assign them things to do.
Like why did name of the leper have to go dip himself in the Jordan seven times?
To be healed.
Right.
Right? What's with Gideon's fleece?
Right? There's all kinds of signs and stuff and these material things that happen
all through the
test of its scriptures. This isn't really different. Okay, if you want to argue to get rid of
Tobit, you can argue on a different basis, but just saying, oh, that's ugly. This is the same kind
of stuff you find in the canonical scriptures, right? So there's not really a difference there.
Also, by the way, Tobit was originally written in Hebrew.
It was not originally written in Greek. We know because we have Hebrew and
and there are make fragments of it in the Dancy Scrolls from Kummer.
Oh, oh, oh.
So that's just a fact, right?
translated into Greek. But anyway, I digress slightly. So,
Tomat does this stuff he's supposed to do with the fish. He could see,
right, and his son, Zalabaric Sarah, because as modius gets banished,
when he gets sort of exercised, he gets sent back to Egypt
and St. Rafael imprisons him in Egypt.
Okay, I know the...
seem like random details, okay? But we're going to get, we're going to do a little,
little mini deep dive here. Shalladive, a mid-range dive right here about esmodius and some of these
little details in Tobit are going to be important. We're going to connect to other things. Okay. So,
as modius, this is one that we haven't talked about before. We've had, we've had some episodes where
we talked about different names for the devil, right? Yeah. And devil figures in second-tempo literature
and in the
Bible like Belial and as Azazel and Satan and the devil and Beals about right we've gone through a bunch of those.
We did run the Antichrist. We haven't talked about Esmodius. So this is this is some different stuff.
So Esmodius he does show up in the Lord of Spirits book everybody. There you put that out there. Yes.
So Esmodius the name as modius is
Not just the name of a French board game company.
It's a, it's the transliteration of Persian pretty much everyone agrees, right?
100% of scholars never agree about anything. There's always a minority report, right?
There's always someone trying to overturn the consensus. But
just about everybody agrees that it is a
transliteration of
Shmadeva.
in Persian becomes as modious in Greek, which literally means in Persian wrath demon,
right, demon of wrath. And so the idea here is that this demon, this demon coming upon someone
is a manifestation of God's wrath. So something sinful has happened, this demon manifests itself,
Right
So this is kind of similar to what's going on with King Saul.
Right. Yeah.
But then as modius, even though he just shows up here in Tobit, has a long afterlife.
Tobit is not part of the Hebrew Canada of the Old Testament, but it has a long afterlife in Judaism.
And through Judaism in Islam and Islam, as modius is a devil figure.
That is the king
of the demons in certain Islamic literature. But this comes by way of the Talmud. And so there
are these various references to Asmodius sort of littered around in the Talmud that reflect
sort of these different earlier traditions, these bits and pieces. And some of these are also
reflected in of all people St. Gregory the Deologist or St. Gregory the Great, the Bishop of Rome,
at the end of the sixth century.
Reflex of these traditions.
So in the Talmud,
As a modious is connected with Solomon's wives in a couple of different ways through a couple
of different traditions.
One of those traditions, he impersonates Solomon, potentially to sleep with his wives.
There are other things going on with Solomon.
We'll get a little more into that here in a minute.
He's also presented at one point as being Mary Delilith.
Oh.
you roll on back to a previous Halloween episode about Lilla Th also.
Yeah.
Um, say, Gregory the Deologist, Bishop Arome, and in the sixth century, talks about
Esmodius and says that he is a fallen throne, which is the third rank, Seraphim
Cherbim and then Thrones, meaning he was a demon connected with a place or a
the nation with ruling up.
place or a nation. And then when you get into medieval Judaism, you find a more developed
bit of tradition that as modius is actually the disembodied spirit of David's Nephilim.
But which we should ever
This is long long pass of a devils Jewish tradition
Can and is yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, so this is not this part is not sick Gregory
Okay, yeah, this is the wow. There's some really interesting fairy tales from the Middle Ages
Well, no, so well, okay
I know there are bits of people much of it's a piece of tradition here, right? Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, I should
More like legend, I think legend, right and I think you can pick up these pieces and you get an idea
you get a shape of something going on in the back.
crown here. Okay. So in that tradition, David slept with Agra, the daughter of Milat,
which is a great name. You do not want to give your daughter this
name. Honey, I was thinking about Agra. Look, Milat. No way. No, you can't. She's, she's
the demon.
who is was considered to be the mate in some sense of Sam Ale.
Yeah, is that the angel of death there?
Sam Ale?
Yes, Sam Ale is the one of the seven archangels who fell in a bunch of traditions, including
St. Gregory the Deologist mentioned Sam Ale.
So we get the picture that St. Gregory at least was conversant in some of these traditions.
And he's living at the end of the sixth century.
So he's verging into the medieval period here.
Yeah, so there's this idea that David is participating
in this kind of pagan sector.
Because Agra was a spirit associated
with Shrine prostitution.
Yeah, yeah.
So the idea here at this tradition is that David
engaged with a Shrine prostitute
of one of the foreign deities at some point in Israel.
and had us.
Sun. Yeah. Okay. This Sun is identified by these Jewish traditions as had the
Edamite who appears in first Kings 11 verse 14 or third kingdoms 11 14. So had
had the Edamite in first Kings is this guy who shows up who he's called had
at the Edamite because he was a member of the Edamite royal family who escaped
to win Joab, David's-
general wiped out the eid of my royal family. He escaped to where? Egypt. Okay. He hit
out in Egypt. Right. And then he comes back to Egypt when he fixed the coast
is clear to try to take that throne and also tries to take the throne of Israel
becomes arrival to Solomon, David's son.
Yeah, yeah.
Okay.
So the idea in this tradition...
is that Hadad the Edomite is David's illegitimate son.
Yeah. Yeah. Through engagement, this temple prostitution, who came out of Egypt, he dies,
right? So some version of the Nephilim ritual, right?
figure out how to eat a bite dies. His spirit is then known as as modius. Right.
who Tobit sends back to, well, who Tobit with St. Rafael send back to Egypt and in prison there.
So with this background, in terms of the story that Tobit is telling,
for the story, Tobit is telling in the third century BC,
The idea is that...
Sarah this woman didn't just get randomly get picked by a demon, right?
To kill all her boyfriend's, right? That wasn't what's going on here.
There was some sinful thing involving shrine prostitution that had gone on.
Yeah.
That had brought this demon to the proximity of her and her family.
Yeah, not necessarily that she was doing.
Right.
Yeah, yeah, certainly not.
You said it is a victim of it.
Yeah, a victim.
Yeah, right. But this is the way a lot of demonic activity works, frankly, is that there's this ancestral element to it.
Of parents and children and parents doing things that the children suffering consequences of it, right.
Um, and so what's happening is that Tobit, his son Tobias and uh, St. Raphael sort of deliver her from this.
Yes.
Whatever this darkness was that brought this demon around.
family, right? And the connection to the demon with Egypt, this had had the
itemite stuff maybe in the background of Tobit, but it's not in the book of
Tobit, right? But I think that Egypt connection is not random. They show the
antiquity of sort of some of those those traditions. So there's that see I think
that bit right there that was worth
price of admission tonight alone. There you go. Right? Like, yeah, are you not entertained? Come on.
So moving from Old Testament, of course, the place where we most see exorcisms in the Bible is in
the synoptic Gospels and Acts. There are no exorcisms in the Gospel of John. But in the synoptic
the Gospels and Acts, there are a lot of them.
We've talked before on the show about the connection between Jesus as the Messiah and this because of particular Psalms of David that were used in the first century.
We know from Kumaaran and other places were used for exorcisms.
So David was this figure associated with exorcism, son of David the Messiah,
similarly, and so part of the reason why the synoptic gospels are presenting Jesus.
performing exorcisms is connected to his Messianic identity as the son of David.
But also we see that this is demonstrated and described as an authority over unclean spirits,
an authority over demons that Jesus possesses and which he then is able to give to his disciples and
apostles. Yeah. Yep. Yep. You have authority over scorpions and serpents and etc. Both the 12 of the
70 are sent out.
right, and then into the book of Acts, right, they continue, right, doing these things.
And we see elements of, in the interactions between the demons and Christ, we see elements,
both of them recognizing his identity, who he is.
And the element of, you are here to trouble us before the time, right, that there is this
period of, there's this end, right?
The devil knows this time is short.
This is a-
into the period of their activity, at which point they will be punished and imprisoned.
But most importantly, both in the case of Christ and his disciples and apostles, the authority
manifests itself as they cast out demons with an authoritative command.
Right.
Now the demons have to obey it because it's Jesus' authority, it's Christ' authority.
That's sort of the important.
the important element there.
And we see there is a distinction though, again,
this is something with Jesus is divine identity inherently possesses, right?
And is able to give the disciples, but the disciples receive it from Jesus.
That kind of is is way clear with the whole episode in the book of Acts with the seven sons of Sceva,
who are going around trying to cast out demons in the name of Jesus who Paul preaches.
Yeah
Yeah.
Trying to use it as like magic words is like a formula.
Right.
And the demon possesses people say, well, Jesus, we know.
And Paul, we've heard of, you know, but who are you
and then proceed to whoop them, to bludgeon them
precipitously about the head and shoulders.
But so in that, right, you notice they say, Jesus, we know.
Right?
They know who he is.
Right.
And they've heard of Paul being finite beings.
Right, they haven't...
met him, but they know who that is, right? But that's not how it works, right? This is
an authority that Christ possesses that he's able to delegate and give to others. But
it's not that his name is magic for this, right? Yeah.
So what does it mean to be possessed by a demon?
Right, we use that term all the time.
Yeah, I think people have this idea like again from movies that demon possession is.
I don't know there's a lot of different things that gets to spinning up.
That's what's about.
Yeah, or you know, you hear voices talking to you or you know, like your body gets animated
by this other force.
Um, yeah, I mean, there's a whole bunch of different weird or you know, talking with the weird voice. Right.
like, these are all things I think that people definitely talking with a weird creepy voice.
Oh, yeah, totally. I mean, without that, you know, it's not. Yeah. Yeah. What did I pay my
ten bucks for this movie for anyway? Yeah. Yeah. So, so is there a difference between
demon possession and like demonic influence? Yes. Is that this? Yeah. Right. To be possessed
by a demon we're talking.
talking about us, we're talking about when spirits are controlling people.
Yeah, talking about a removal of agency from the person.
So the person is just acting on demonic impulses.
Yeah, it's not, it's not just like being tempted.
You know, yeah, not just thoughts.
It's not just even like feeling afflicted or whatever.
It's really like handing over, you know, like, like a demon is using your body,
like a mech from the person is out of control.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, just acting based on right and it's the comparison is
Right if if you know a person cannot
voluntarily
You can't hold your breath until you die
Right you literally can't
right
and
If you get even remotely close your body itself goes into this state of desperation where you will gasp for air
Right, beyond your control. Right. Or if a person is legitimately starving, right?
Like legitimately on the verge of starving the death and you put food in front of them, they will eat that food.
Right. Right. Whatever it is. Right. There's, there's not a right. And so that kind of loss of control is the loss of spiritual loss of control we're talking about with the monocosession.
right where it's
just acting on these demonic impulses immediately.
There's no like thought and consideration, right?
It's just an immediate action, right?
Another way of thinking about it might be addiction, right?
At a certain point, you're choosing to drink
or to take a drink or to use a drug.
At a certain point, though, down the road of that,
you're not choosing anymore.
Yeah, it over.
your will on you know little by little like he erodes your will initially but but yeah it puts you
into that state of physical desperation right that's what we're talking about right is that happening
with a demonic spirit in the driver's seat right right and then of course represents a reduction
of humanity.
Yeah, it's a subhuman state.
That's...
That's why when we see demon possessed people like in the synoptic gospels, they're like living
among the tombs, right, running around naked, right, living like animals, right, in this
subhuman state.
And this is what we're talking about, fallen humanity.
This is fallen humanity, right, the imaging of God, right, the ability to image God has
been sort of given up.
Yeah.
And there's a continuum of this, you know, so, but with demonic possession, we're talking
really extreme pushed way, way down the continuum. But that is not the most extreme state.
No, there is a worse. Yes, it could be there is a worst state, right? Because the demon
possessed person needs to be delivered from the demon. Yes, right. In the same way that
right, the person in any of those other states of desperation needs to have their affliction removed.
Right? Like they need to be fed or they need air or they need to break the addiction.
Right? Same kind of thing. They need to be delivered from the evil spirit.
The step worse than that is where a person is still fully in control and has their will functioning,
but voluntarily agrees with the demons.
Yeah, you're synergizing with the demon.
They align their will with these demonic spirits and what they want to do.
there's not a way out of control at acting on the demons prompting it's their fully un...
Yeah, they're not enslaved. They're partners. And this is what we're talking about, we're talking about giants.
We're talking about Nephilim. Yeah, which is what we're talking about.
Emphasized that as you said earlier, I think in the episode, but and as we said before,
you know, these giants, Nephilim, these demonized people are not truly the kind of
of product of a particular ritual or whatever.
Yes, that ritual can be involved in that person's life and can be kind of the start of this relationship that they have with the demon, but you can get there in other ways.
It's really just about aligning your will with the demonic will.
And if Sarah in Tobit had decided to agree with the demon, didn't look at it as an affliction.
Yeah, right
Had become demonic herself. That's what we
be talking about, but she didn't, right? It was an affliction. It was something she
needed to be delivered from and saved from, right? Right. Right. And, you know, in Orthodox
Christianity, we talk about like the path of salvation is the path of synergy with God.
Like you energize with God's energy. Your will aligns with God's will. You do, you know,
you do his works, whatever. Your activity. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. But, but there is an opposite
approach. You can synergize with demons. I've had, I said this, some, I can't remember where it was
was somewhere on social media.
I said that and someone was like, no, synergies.
word that only applies to what we do with God. And, and you know, when we were talking about this
earlier, Father, you pointed out to me, actually, actually, in second, the Athosolony Institute.
Oh, actually. Yeah. Yeah. Exactly. And second, this is two nine, talk about the anti-Christ,
the man of lawlessness. St. Paul says that this man of lawlessness says, who's coming is after the
working of Satan with all power and signs and lying wonders. And that phrase, after the working of
Satan.
is caught and then and then again to satanah. So according to the energies of Satan of the Satan.
So yeah, that's synergy with the Satan right there. Right. I mean, yeah.
And it's not it's not a magical thing. Like it's just your will.
It's the Antichrist. Right.
is you're willing to participate in the energies of the devil. Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah, and so there is this sort of spectrum and on one end of the spectrum you have temptation,
right?
Thoughts coming into our heads, right?
The event's putting thoughts into our heads.
Everybody experiences this.
Right.
And then you have the next step is sort of demonic torment, like what we see with Saul, right?
where these thoughts we don't handle and deal with correctly.
right? And so they start generating synonyms like anger, right? And
early. Yeah. And start spiraling. Then the next step past that is
possession. And then the final step of the other extreme from
temptation is participation. Yeah, that's the that's the
Nephilim level. Yeah, giant land. Yeah. And there are not a lot
of these people, but there are these
people. Yeah, we could call them ghouls. They're for two. Well, I mean, they don't even have to be
lit. Well, I was about to say, I've only ever met one in my life. It was in a prison and
he had engaged in an act of cannibalism. So there you go. I'm about to say they aren't necessarily
cannibals, but there you go. But so yeah, there are these people, right? They're very rare. Thank God.
Right.
But that that's the spectra we just talked about from temptation on the one end to participation really is a question of one way of looking at it is how much humanity how much imaging God is left.
So you could be a very holy person and face temptation.
Of course the Lord himself that's why it's at the one that's why it's at the one extreme right.
participation, right? When you're at that
level, when you're like the antigrist to giant level, you have, as St. John
Chris Awesome says, essentially become a demon.
Honor, you've become one yourself essentially.
Yeah, you don't, it's not that you change into another nature.
He says this is not that you change natures is says that your, your energy,
your functioning becomes just like theirs.
Yeah.
And so at that point, your humanity is all but gone.
Right.
And that's why one of the
ways that the internal condemnation that such a person might face at the
judgment seat of Christ is referred to in the Orthodox Church by some fathers as
sort of a loss of humanity. That whatever bit little bit is left before the
judgment, right, that's sort of the consequence at the judgment. That whatever
little humanity has left is lost. But anyone at any point in the spectrum, and
And yes, I'm including.
those people in that participation level, in that giant level, in that level.
Any of them, as long as they're alive, can find repentance through the power of God.
Yes. There's no one who in this life is hopeless.
Right. I mean, and we see people up to the giant level in the Scriptures being delivered,
including, you know, Legion being possessed by you know.
Yeah, hundreds of demons being delivered from that.
Yeah, right.
So that's a, that's a thing.
Um,
so, uh,
this gets into then.
So how is,
how exorcism works?
Right.
We, we had a couple of questions in the chat asking about exorcism.
So I'm sorry, go everybody.
And how we understand exorcism, right?
But it's based on what we just said.
Right? So, exorcism is going to be a way of dealing with, right, the demonic influence on a person.
Anywhere across that spectrum, you can describe it as exorcism. Okay?
But so, what we just said about that spectrum, then it's going to color how we see exorcism.
So we do exorcism at baptisms famously.
right? Yeah.
Getting of the orthodox
vegetable services and
exorcism.
Which people will ask like,
wait, are you saying the baby is
demon possessed or whoever is
coming to baptism is demon
possessed?
No, but they're at least on
the temptation level of the
spectrum.
Right. I mean, they're living in a
world where they're being where
demons are attacking them
like we all.
Right. If you're anywhere
out of that spectrum,
right, there's demonic activity
around you, right?
And the exorcism is dealing
with that.
Right. Now
Now that included in the
church, you know, adults who were full on demon possessed. Absolutely. Yes. Right. Or who had been.
Right. And we're now maybe tormented. Right. They're pagan days. They had been possessed
and now in there after their years of repentance to come into the church, they're more at the
tormented stage. But we're still dealing with that with this exorcism. Right. Before baptism.
And we talked about cleansing and doing an exercise.
amount of place, right? We're doing exorcism prayers with people. The important thing is that
the exorcism is not dealing with some kind of psychological state.
Yeah, it's not the person. Feel better. Now you might feel better.
But that's not the point. That's a consequence. That's not what's going on.
Right. I mean, I hope so. You get these people, Bob Larson, who
Go around taking money from benign people who want to come and offer them, you know, who have, you know, the demon of overeating or the demon of self-esteem for him to like smack up in the head and tell him it's cast out of them.
Okay, that's a grift.
That's got nothing to do with actual exorcism.
That's got nothing to do with any of this, okay?
It's not all we're talking about.
Well,
What we're talking about is, exercise is a way of dealing with sin and its consequences.
And one of the consequences of sin is enslavement to sin.
And enslavement to the demonic powers.
That's one of the consequences.
And so that slavery needs to be broken.
The person who has the authority to do it is Christ.
And
the exorcism ritual, whether it's in baptism, whether it's outside of baptism, whether it's the
exorcism place, it's about breaking that connection, right? Breaking that chain that's been forged by
sin. So this is all within the context of sin and repentance, not magic, not psychology, not feelings,
right but in the realm of sin and its consequences and one of those in
particular. Yeah. Yeah. Well, as we're wrapping up this pretty exciting in some ways,
episode of the Laura Spirits podcast, we have a lot of good calls tonight too. Yeah, I,
well, you know, like I said, a number of you in the chat on YouTube, we're asking about
and we kind of finished up there.
And yes, I mean number one are liturgical acts of x-
that priest or bishop performs, as he said, with baptisms in some special cases if someone is
evidencing,
evencing demonic possession, but also house blessings. Like this is the time of year a lot of people getting their houses blessed.
So all of that is there, these priestly acts.
But I also want to kind of extend that out a little bit
because I know that
Here, my sense is that right now there's a lot of people who are worried about demonic activity and maybe experiencing it in a way that they haven't in the past or perceiving it in a way that they haven't in the past.
Sometimes because they are someone they know was quite deliberately involving themselves in it, like in the occult or witchcraft or whatever it might be.
Fortune telling mediums, you know, etc.
And...
And you might ask, well, okay, all right, I, yes, I need to connect with a priest and
an ex, you know, and have to be baptized or to have my house blessed or whatever is needed.
But then also just because that happens, right, that doesn't mean that all the temptations
are going to go away.
It doesn't mean that all of your bad habits are going to go away.
It doesn't mean that experiences that you have of maybe even
being tormented by spiritual attacks are going to go away.
Right?
So the question is, well, how do I live now?
What do I do?
I think this is one of the big questions of our moment in history that we are at.
What am I supposed to do?
And the good news is that there's not some kind of special formula or technique or method
What you're supposed to do is to live the Christian life, like be baptized, become part
of the church, live in repentance, live in faithfulness.
All of the things that are the normal Christian life, worship together with other believers,
prayer together with your family at home, prayer privately, reading the scriptures and
You know, participating in the FASTs
engaging in almsgiving and acts of active love and charity.
These are the, this is the Christian life, right? These sticks. And the beautiful thing,
what are the beautiful things about this? As you live this way, as you put your life in order,
as you put your house in order, you put, you know, your family in order, all these things,
these are all exorcistic acts. All these things are exorcistic, meaning that they drive out
demonic inflow.
because there's no neutrality. There's no neutrality. The way that you drive out
demonic influence the way you drive out, synergizing with devils is by
synergizing with God, doing his works, participating in what he wills, and
that elevates the human person. He heals the human person, right? That's how it
works. That doesn't mean there's not going to be temptations. I mean, even we can see
with a very very
holy people, super holy people, very advanced, they can still be attacked by demons. But the outcome
is going to be very different than someone who's saying, okay, well let's do that bad thing,
the evil thing. So that's what I want to leave folks with is that the normal everyday ordinary
acts of Christian life.
actually electrified with spiritual power because Christ said that he would give us grace
and save us through our faithfulness.
So what do you have to say, Father Stephen?
So yeah, related to that, there's this statement Christ makes about.
exorcisms where he talks about how if you exercise a demon the demon goes into these very dry places
right out of the desert you cast out into the desert out into the wilderness out into the place of evil
right but if there's not any kind of change in the person then it just comes back and moves in
with seven of its friends. Right, and the person's worse off than they were before.
And I think we've maybe taken what Christ is saying there too literally.
As they and we've said, well, I haven't literally had any demons cast out of me.
So this verse doesn't apply to me.
This is kind of an obscure and just thing.
But what Christ is actually talking about is something, because remember, demonic influence
is this spectrum, right?
He's really talking about something that we've all experienced and that's that a lot of
this stuff keeps coming back.
I could pretty confidently say that there's probably no one listening to this who's an
Orthodox Christian or probably a Roman Catholic either who meaning they go to confession who
Hasn't had to go back and confess the same things over and over and over again
And you don't want them to come back.
That's where the reasons you're bringing them up in confession.
You don't, right?
You don't want them to come back.
You want them to be gone.
You want to be done with this for good.
You want to never do this again and fall into it again.
And it comes back.
And sometimes it gets worse.
And at the core, as hard as it is for us to hear, the core reason that keeps us going
happening is that while we don't want it to come back, we don't want to do the work
that would be required for it not to come back. We want the results without the effort.
We want confession to sort of be magic. There I said it. I said it out loud that I did
this. I don't want to do it anymore. Now I want to never be tempted again.
Now I never want to have to think about this again. Now I never want to have to worry about this again.
Now are you able to just go through life blissfully peaceful?
Uh, never, never falling back into sin.
But, but that requires hard work.
Right? Because
all of these things that we've fallen prey to, all of these places where
to whatever degree might be a small degree, might be a larger degree,
We've given these powers, we've given our enemies.
You have enemies.
If you don't have any visible ones,
you have invisible ones.
Who are out to throw stumbling blocks in our path,
who are out to trip us up,
who are out to destroy us ultimately.
Every little bit of turf in our life,
every little piece where we've given them some control
and a foothold and a fingerhold, right?
All of those places, even if,
He will
Then if the power of God comes in and uproots it, Christ has warned us if we don't then
make the changes we need to make, if we don't then fix the things we need to fix, they're
just going to come right back.
And maybe worse.
Right?
And these changes we need to make in our life, right?
You've got a life that's full of all kinds of things.
Some of those things are sinful and bad.
Part of the problem is we try to replace those with nothing.
I say to people in confession a lot, right?
If you try to avoid this sin that you're struggling with by sitting in your room and staring at a wall,
that ain't gonna work.
Right?
If you try to replace something negative, something bad, something evil with nothing,
something insidious with nothing,
It's not going to go anywhere.
You have to replace it with something positive.
I'm going to double down on what we said last time.
Positive does not mean overtly Christian or overtly orthodox Christian.
If the temptation you face requires you to go off by yourself and spend time alone, then
One of the best things you can replace that with is just spending time with other
people, spending time with family members, spending time with friends, out with them in
public, right?
Spending time in real space with humans, going to church activities, going to other things,
right?
Thereby, removing you from that situation in which you are tempted and filling your life
with something good, even though it's common, it's still good.
if you're done you don't have to be talking about spiritual things played
hearts. Right? Dare I say it, play cards, sorry, Baptist. Oh, no. Right? Send me a friend
request and play Marvel rivals. Right? Just do something. Right? That is good and
friendly and right and and and even if it's common, right, that isn't sinful. Right? Fill
your life with those things and with good things.
And that will help find a temptation.
And then when those things that have be deviled you, pun intended, in the past, come back,
right, and try to get that hold again and try to get that grip again, they'll find that the handles they used to use are now gone.
The levers they used to pull, right?
Unfortunately for us, our enemies are really crafty and they'll find other ways.
and we'll have to repeat this process and we'll have to keep doing it and it's something we'll have to work
on our whole life, right? But if you're feeling like a failure and you're feeling like you're
trapped in a cycle and you're feeling like you can't get anywhere, this is how to do it.
At least this way you'll face new challenges and new struggles, instead of the same old ones over
and over again. So those are my final thoughts. Thank you for that. Well, that's our show tonight,
everybody we appreciate you showing up and listening.
If you didn't get through to us live, we'd select to hear from you.
You can email us at LordofSpiritsNationFace.com.
You can message us at our Facebook page.
You can also leave us a voice mail at SpeakPipe.com slash LordofSpirits.
And you have basic questions about Orthodox Christianity or you need help in finding a 3D
real life in-person parish.
Head over to OrthodoxInchro.org.
Enjoy this for our live broadcast on the second and fourth Thursdays of the month at 7PM
Eastern 4PM Pacific.
you see more of me, cobwebs in the way.
If you're on Facebook you can follow our page, you can join our discussion group, leave
all those ratings and reviews and all the places and most importantly share this show with
a friend who is going to benefit from it.
I'd be sure to go to www.inxiofate.com, support it, help make sure we and lots of other AFR
podcasters stay on the air.
The Magic Cleaner will shine a smile on me.
Thank you, good night.
God bless you.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits with Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew
Stephen Damick and Father Stephen De Young, a listener-supported presentation of ancient faith radio.
And I be held, and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne and the beasts
and the elders.
And the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000 and thousands of thousands, saying with
loud voice. Worthy is the
land that was slain to receive power and riches and wisdom and strength and honor and glory and blessing.
Revelation chapter 5